Kiss
Kiss
We welcome Vice President Lee to host the performance of in national talent competition
We welcome Vice President Lee to host the performance of in national talent competition
Hu Yu for
Hu Yu for
Welcome Vice President tree
Welcome Vice President tree
Extra
Extra
The speakers of our session will be
The speakers of our session will be
report EI ONS is the same as NZ Hi
ReporteionShen Zhiyang
The speaker of our session will be
The speaker of our session will be
depth ty peugeot
Deputy Pujo
This
This
Senator
Senator
Colleagues in the hospital and our friends from Academia Sinica
院內的同仁 還有我們中央研究院的朋友們
good night everyone
大家晚安 大家好
I am very glad that you all come to our Academia Sinica today
今天很高興大家來參加我們中央研究院
Feast of knowledge in November this year
今年度11月份的知識饗宴
We all enjoyed a very sumptuous dinner just now
剛才我們大家都享受了一個很豐盛的晚餐
But apart from this bodily feast
但是除了這一個肉體上的這個饗宴以外
More importantly, we have a feast of knowledge
更重要的是我們要有知識的饗宴
So we are very happy that you can come to participate today
所以我們今天很高興大家能夠來參加
Let's try, psychologically and intellectually
讓我們在審理 心理 還有知識上
Both can improve, both can increase our own nutrition
都能夠有所提升 都能夠增加我們自己的營養
Let me briefly introduce our speaker today
我簡單的來介紹一下今天我們的演講者
Today we are very happy to invite you to our Central Research Institute
今天我們很高興請到我們中央研究院
Researcher and Deputy Director of the Institute of Biomedical Sciences
生物醫學科學研究所的研究員兼副所長
Deputy director Shen Zhiliang came to tell us all
沈志良副所長來跟我們大家講
Health issues that everyone cares about
大家很關心的健康上的問題
is to tailor your health
就是量身打造你的健康
Personal Medicine in the 21st Century
二十一世紀的個人醫學
We often say, oops, why would someone have two meetings earlier?
我們常常說 哎呀 為什麼有人會早兩會三
some people get this disease some people get that disease
會生這個病 有人會生那個病
Because everyone's illness is different
因為每一個人生病的狀況都會不一樣
Then when SARS came
然後SARS來了以後
Some people get sick and some don't
有人會發病 有人不會發病
So what is the reason?
那到底什麼原因呢
What about our Chinese medicine?
那我們中國的醫藥呢
called Chinese medicine
就叫做中醫
different personalities
就叫做個人體質不同
Personal physique is different
個人體質不同裡面
Actually there is an important one
其實有很重要的一個
Just the genetics may be different
就是遺傳基因可能不一樣
Are genetic diseases related to human diseases?
那遺傳基因到底有跟人類的疾病
what is the relationship
有什麼關係
We are the deputy director of the province
這個我們是省副所長
He is at the Academia Sinica
他在中央研究院
the research done
所做的這個研究
They are all very unique insights in this regard.
都是這方面很有獨到的見解
He was in 1983 and 1987
他在1983年跟1987年
from the National Taiwan University of Public Health
從國立台灣大學的公共衛生
After graduating from departments and graduate schools
學系跟研究所畢業以後
Go to North Carolina in the United States to train a doctor
就到美國的北卡訓練博士
So back after the Ph.D.
所以回到博士學位以後
has been in our Central Research Institute
就一直在我們中央研究院
Research Fellow at the Institute of Biomedical Sciences
生物醫學科學研究所擔任研究員
His research is quite outstanding
他的研究相當的傑出
so what
那所以呢
he has been all the way
他一路以來
Both left molecular and genetic epidemiology
都在左分子跟遺傳的流行病學
He is an internationally renowned scholar
他是一個國際知名的學者
Let me give you an example like the research on breast cancer that I will talk about later.
舉一個例子像等一下要講的這個乳癌的研究
In addition to doing a good job with domestic breast cancer research
他除了用國內的乳癌的研究做得很好以外
We also participate in international cooperation projects
也參加國際的合作計畫
is the first global team
是第一個全球的團隊
To perform a full gene scan on the genes of breast cancer patients
去對乳癌的病人的基因做全基因的掃描
To find the gene for this heterosensitivity
去找到這個異感受的基因
He will share with you today
他今天會跟大家分享
Then we all often take medicine and say
那我們大家常常吃藥說
Oops, this A.R.M.A. eats watermelon Huan Jane
哎呀 這個A.R.M.A.吃西瓜 歡簡
That means we often take medicine
那就是說我們常常吃藥
Sometimes there are side effects and some people don't
有些時候會有副作用 有些人不會
What are the side effects of this drug?
那這副作用的藥物的副作用
what genes are affected
影響的基因是什麼
Here's the research their team did
這是他們的團隊所做的研究
this research is very important
這個研究很重要
Admire the best clinical research in the world
登在世界最好的臨床醫學的研究
Beyond New Eagle Liver Medicine
新鷹肝醫學雜誌以外
It is important that the results of this study
很重要的這一個研究的結果
Also makes the US Drug Inspection Bureau say
也使美國的藥物實病檢驗局說
When you want to take a certain medicine in the future
未來要吃某一種藥的時候
which gene to test
就要檢驗哪一個基因
have this genotype
有這個基因型的
it can't be like this
就不可以是這個樣
because of serious side effects
因為會有很嚴重的副作用
It has made a great contribution to the care of mankind.
那對人類的照顧是有很大很大的貢獻
So we are very happy to invite the priest and director today
所以我們今天很高興請到神父所長
Come give us a talk like this
來跟我們做這樣的一個演講
Let me tell you a little secret
那給大家講一個小祕密
Father and Director, besides doing a good job in research
神父所長他除了研究做得很好以外
he is internationally renowned
他國際知名以外
He is also the winner of many domestic academic awards
他也是國內很多學術獎的得獎者
He is the recipient of the National Science Council's Relief Award.
他是國科會的解除獎的得獎者
Then in mid-December when he
然後他在12月中的時候
I want to take this from Wang Mingning
要拿這個王明寧的
Outstanding Research Contribution Award
傑出研究的貢獻獎
That is the highest award in the civil state of Washington, second only to the President's Award
那個是僅次於總統獎的民間華州最高的這個獎項
so we welcome him to speak to us
所以我們歡迎他來跟我們演講
Congratulations to his award
也恭喜他的獎
OK
好不好
Thank you Father Dean for your introduction
謝謝神父院長的介紹
I am very happy that today our good friends inside and outside the courtyard
那很高興今天我們院內院外的好朋友
tonight
今天晚上
I hope to be able to give everyone a
我希望能夠大家給大家一個
What the priest and dean said just now
剛才神父院長講的
A rewarding evening in every way
在各方面都有收穫的一個晚上
Then I'll give you a very simple start
那我就給大家一個很簡單的開始
Because it is now 100 years since the founding of the country
因為現在建國100年
There is a national movement in this place
這個地方都有國動
Among them, the State Council of the Forbidden City has the so-called wonderful 100
那其中故宮國務院有所謂的精彩100
There is the National Security Agency
有那個國保總動員
that was a few days ago
那在前幾天
I went with my father-in-law and mother-in-law to see the national security guards in the Forbidden City
我跟我的岳父岳母去看故宮的國保
One of the interesting words is
其中有一個很有趣的話就是
One from the Southern Song Dynasty is called Jia Sigu
南宋的一個叫賈斯古一個
painter
畫家
He drew a painting called Yanguan Ancient Temple
他畫了一個叫做延觀古寺
Then this ancient temple of Yanguan is known to many people in China better than me
那這幅延觀古寺是中國很多人比我更了解
Our Chinese landscape painting is a very important boutique
我們中國那個山水畫一個很重要的精品
He painted that pine
他畫那個松啊
On that rugged mountain
在那個很崎嶇的山上啊
This temple is very famous
這個一個廟非常的有名
Look at the lower left corner in Jasko
那在賈斯古大家看那個左下角
Jascu also put himself
賈斯古還把他自己
leave your name on it
自己的名字留在上面
Well, of course I don't have an artistic flair.
那當然我沒什麼文藝氣息啊
I love this painting
我對這個護畫
really make me
真的讓我
most interested in
感到最有興趣的是
These two things in the lower right corner
右下角這兩個東西
it looks like you zoomed in on it
看起來你把它放大
like the guy in the transformers
像那個變形金剛裡面的人
And think what is this
而且想 欸 這個是什麼
Then someone told me
後來有人跟我講說
Ah, this thing, that is
啊 這個東西喔 那是
Judgment of Yang Ling's only breath is too bad
審治陽靈唯一氣息太差
What are you actually?
你這個東西喔 事實上就是什麼
Just look at the Qingming River Scene
就是你看那個清明上河圖
right there
就是在那個
Our most original Song Dynasty Zhang Zheduan's Qingming Riverside Picture
我們最原版的宋朝張哲端的清明上河圖
Qingming Shanghe map has
清明上河圖有
The part with the bridge and the part with the river
有過橋的部分 有河的部分
and that part of the street
以及那個大街的部分
on this street
在這條大街上面
Hey there is a person
欸 有一個人
you magnify it
你把它放大
What is that, ancient stranger?
那個就是什麼 古代的生人
So it turns out that Gu Sigu painted this thing just now.
原來剛才那個賈斯古畫的這個東西喔
It's a stranger, it's just used oblique
就是生人 那只是用比較斜
That abstract method draws it
那個抽象的方法把它畫出來
It's a person with this thing on it
就是一個人上面還有這個東西
so it looks like a transformer
所以看起來像變形金剛
That's why Justin draws it more clearly
那因此 賈斯尼把它畫得更清楚
It's the one in the Qingming River Scene
就是清明上河圖裡面這個
In ancient times, in my current words, monks
古代的跟我現在的話來講 就和尚
the monk of course
那這個和尚 當然
make it more
再把它更
see that clearly
那個清楚來看
Hezang in Tang Dynasty and Song Dynasty
當時候唐朝宋朝河藏
Of course the most famous monk is Tang Sanzang
當然最有名的和尚就是唐三藏
take seven days
去七天取
Tangshan Tibet in Dunhuang Dihua
在敦煌帝化裡面的唐山藏
He also brought one like the one at that time
他也是帶一個像當時候的那個
That's the same. He bid farewell to the Tang Dynasty emperor and said
那個一樣他拜別那個唐朝皇帝說
I'm going to the West to learn Buddhist scriptures
我要去西天取經了
so be yourself
所以就自有樣子
what does this have to do with us tonight
那這跟我們今天晚上有什麼樣的
relevance
的關聯性
I thought of one thing with this
我用這個想到一件事情
That is to say, we all have a Buddha
就是說我們大家有佛
That buddhist friend wants to say
那個佛教的朋友都想說
Buddhism teaches that all beings should be equal
佛教是在講眾生要平等
so can't kill
所以不能夠殺生
So Buddhism cannot eat that animal
所以佛教不能夠吃那個動物
But in fact the habit of being a vegetarian in Buddhism
可是事實上佛教來吃素這個習慣
In fact, from the Tang Dynasty
事實上是從唐朝開始
Because from the past, although Buddhism can say
因為從過去雖然佛門可以說
try not to kill
盡量不要殺生
But it's really going to be the time of the two and five emperors
可是真的要到兩五帝的那個時候
That's why we in Buddhism can't kill
才說那個我們佛教不能夠殺生
As long as the Tang Dynasty
一隻要到唐朝
Buddhist vegetarianism has only begun to become a
佛教吃素才開始變成一種
Now everyone agrees that the one on the Niguel River
現在大家認定說那個尼古河上
Can't just eat vegetables
不能夠只能夠吃菜
Can't be vegetarian
不能夠吃素
Then this thing is important to our medicine
那這個東西對我們醫學
A big influence is
一個很大的影響是
Vegetarian thing
吃素這件事情
Thinking about it now is a healthy thing
現在想起來都是一件健康的事
why is it healthy
為什麼是健康的事呢
Then let’s talk about the Vice President Chen’s speech just now.
那就拉到剛才那個陳副院長講
Specialized in my laboratory research
我實驗室研究的專門
breast cancer in girls
是研究女生乳癌
Was there any breast cancer in the Tang and Han Dynasties?
在唐朝漢朝有沒有乳癌的
Yes, I have
有啊
In the Song Dynasty there was one of the oldest
在宋朝有一本最古老的
The Treasures of Chinese Surgery
中國的外科學的寶典
It's called "Unrecorded Treasure Book"
就是叫做《未記寶書》
in this book
在這本書當中
In fact, in Chinese history
事實上是在中國歷史上面
the word cancer
第一個癌這個字
was in AD 1170
是在西元1170年
it really started to have the word cancer
它真的開始有這個癌這個字
that in this book
那在這個這本書當中
also began to point out a phenomenon
也開始指出一個現象
That phenomenon is our epidemiological
那個現象就是我們流行病學
The golden rule that is often said nowadays
現在常常講的金科玉律
that is, breast cancer
就是說乳癌
The incidence of breast cancer in girls is 40 years old
女生乳癌的發生是40歲
You see this is the incidence of so-called common cancers
你看這是所謂的常見癌症的發生率
Female breast cancer after the age of 40
女性乳癌到40歲之後
began to happen gradually
就開始逐漸的發生
In this China's oldest
在這本中國最古老的
It is mentioned in ancient surgical books that
古老的外科學書當中就提到說
Girls' breast cancer will start to climb gradually after the age of 30 or 40
女生的乳癌在三四十歲之後就會開始逐漸爬升
And it took about three years to become ill
而且病成大概是三年
then i put
那我把
just said
剛才講說
Buddhism says to be vegetarian
佛教說要吃素
breast cancer
跟這個女生乳癌
get together
湊在一起
It is one of our medical
就是我們醫學當中一個
What is often seldom observed before is the
常常很少以前就觀察到的現象就是
nun
尼姑
Nun because he is in Buddhism
尼姑他因為在佛門
he doesn't eat meat
他不吃肉
so he is vegetarian
因此他只吃素
But this vegetarian
可是這種吃素的
that is to say girls
的就是說女生
Don't nuns get married and don't have children?
尼姑不結婚嗎不生小孩
Usually wait and see
一般等一下會看到
Girls who don't have children are more likely to get breast cancer
不生小孩的女生通常很容易得乳癌
But Nun Nico
可是尼哥尼姑
he does not have children
他不生小孩
But his chance of getting breast cancer is much lower than the average person
可是他得乳癌的機率是遠遠低於一般人
so everyone wants
因此大家是想
Nuns and ordinary girls
尼姑跟一般女生
The biggest difference between a nun and ordinary girls is that he does not eat meat
尼姑跟一般女生最大的差別是他不吃肉
therefore
因此
Being vegetarian can prevent girls from getting breast cancer
吃素可以預防女生不得乳癌這件事情
rare
很少
Everyone had this idea before
以前大家就這個想法
Then we put our observations
那我們把我們的觀察
From the Tang Dynasty to the Song Dynasty
從當時候的唐朝宋朝
Get our Taiwan today
拿到我們今天的台灣
This is our girl from Taiwan
這是我們台灣地區女生
incidence of common cancers
常見癌症的發生率
you can find
你可以發現
Uterine Well Cancer Because of Lifestyle Habits
子宮井癌因為生活習慣
Improvement in Hygiene Habits
衛生習慣的改善
Uterine well cancer is getting lower and lower
子宮井癌越來越低
But breast cancer is increasing
可是乳癌越來越高
Breast cancer is now a common cause of girls in Taiwan
乳癌現在是台灣地區女生
Ranked by incidence
發生率排名的
cancer number one
第一號癌症
is a very important
是一個很重要的
public health issues
公共衛生問題
Therefore standing on a medical
因此站在一個醫學的
researchers would like to say
研究學者就會想說
why is it getting higher and higher
為什麼越來越高
In fact the answer
事實上這個答案
Since then on the Niguel
從當時候尼古河上
already told us
已經告訴我們了
Let's see again because of breast cancer
因為乳癌我們再來看
a structure of our breasts
一個我們的乳房的構造
The structure of our breasts
我們的乳房的構造
like our lungs
就像我們的肺臟一樣
like big trees
就像大樹木一樣
big trees with big limbs
大樹木有大肢幹
is the structure of milk ducts
就是乳管的構造
What is breast cancer in the structure of milk ducts
乳管的構造當中乳癌是什麼
Breast cancer refers to the structure of these milk ducts
乳癌就是指這些乳管構造當中的
A certain cell starts from one to two and two to four
某一個細胞開始一個變兩個兩個變四個
until the end of the milk duct is full
到最後把整個乳管的塞滿
run out at the end
到最後再跑出去
You use that histology section to say
你用那個組織學的切片就是說
Suppose a breast cancer patient you cut a piece of cancer tissue
假設一個乳癌病人你切一塊癌症組織
You can see that the normal milk duct is everyone
你就看到說正常的乳管就是大家
Below you can see that this is very similar to a pipe-by-pipe situation
下面看到這個很像一個管子一個管子的情形
Let's talk about cancer cells starting to grow randomly
那我們講說開始癌細胞就開始亂長
always long long long
一直一直長長長長
Fill the whole breast cancer
把整個乳癌的塞滿
We call it original cancer
我們就稱為叫原味癌
It looks like you see here on the right
看起來就像大家右手邊看到這裡一樣
It's the whole thing full of you see
就是整個的塞滿你看
Originally, the milk ducts were empty because of the absence of milk
本來乳管人家空空的因為產生無乳
But primary cancer is to fill up the entire milk duct
可是原味癌就是把整個乳管的塞滿
Once penetrated, it becomes a cancer cell
一旦穿透出去就變成癌細胞
running around
到處跑來跑去的樣子
This is breast cancer as we know it
這個就是我們所認識的乳癌
Through our awareness of breast cancer
藉由我們這個認識的乳癌
We explain why breast cancer is on the rise
我們了解說為什麼現在乳癌越來越高
Because one of the leading causes of breast cancer
因為乳癌一個最主要的原因
female hormone
就是女性荷爾蒙
It's a chemical mask like this
它的化學口罩就這樣子
because it's simple
因為很簡單
boys and girls
男生跟女生
The difference between girls is that boys are almost free from breast cancer
女生差別是男生幾乎不得乳癌
Girls are prone to breast cancer
女生很容易得乳癌
Where is the difference between boys and girls
男生女生差別在哪裡
boys do not menstruate
男生沒有月經
Girls have menstruation
女生有月經啊
when girls menstruate
女生月經的時候
In our warm tide will produce this female hormone
在我們的暖潮就會產生這個女性荷爾蒙
What is the main function of female hormones
女性荷爾蒙的主要的功能是什麼
We have female hormones to thank
我們要感謝女性荷爾蒙
Because female hormones go to our breast cells
因為女性荷爾蒙跑到我們的乳房細胞
Estrogen travels to the cells of our uterus
女性荷爾蒙跑到我們的子宮的細胞
will make one cell become two
會讓細胞一個變兩個
two to four
兩個變四個
where is the purpose
目的在哪裡
The purpose is to replace the fetus that may come
目的在替可能來到的胎兒
build a house first
先蓋一個家
you want
你要
The fetus is about to implant in the womb
胎兒要著床在子宮
Then of course we have to build a home for him first.
那當然要先蓋一個家給他
So the role of the hormone itself is
因此荷爾蒙本身的角色就是
sudden death breast cells
猝死乳房細胞
sudden death endometrial cell proliferation
猝死子宮內膜細胞不斷的增生
to give a girl a chance to meet
來讓一個女生有機會迎接
coming baby
將要來到的寶寶
But this situation
可是這個情形
Know the cancer cells
就給癌細胞認識了
what do we say cancer cells
我們說癌細胞是什麼
cancer cell
癌細胞就是指細胞亂
I just mentioned this situation
剛才講到這個情形
so would have been a good thing
因此本來的一件好事
Hypothetically for cancer cells to take advantage of
假設給癌細胞利用了
A normal cell
本來一個細胞正常的情形
Assuming that after giving it to cancer cells to steal it
假設給癌細胞把它偷走之後
Cancer cells say I will use it
癌細胞說我就利用
This hormone prompts the cells
這個赫爾蒙會觸使細胞
This property of proliferation
增生的這個特性
that can easily lead to breast cancer
那就很容易導致乳癌的發生
because girls have this
因為女生有這個
So girls get breast cancer
所以女生會得乳癌
boys don't have this
男生沒有這個
Boys don't get breast cancer
男生不會得乳癌
Then you say that this air belt causes breast cancer
那你說這根氣帶乳癌發生
What does it matter if you get higher and higher
越來越高有什麼關係
That's the clue the nun told us
那個就是尼姑告訴我們的線索
because where does hermon come from
因為赫爾蒙哪裡來
The source of hormone is from our cholesterol
赫爾蒙的來源是來自於我們的膽固醇
where does cholesterol come from
膽固醇哪裡來
Cholesterol is in western food
膽固醇就是西方食物當中
high fat content
含量比較多的脂肪
So Nidi gradually became smaller
所以尼底逐漸些小
Why now breast cancer is getting higher and higher
現在為什麼現在乳癌越來越高
or you said just now
或者是你說剛才
Why nuns are less likely to get breast cancer
尼姑為什麼比較不容易得乳癌
Because the nun is vegetarian?
因為尼姑吃素嘛
vegetarian results
吃素的結果
leading to their lower fat intake
導致他們脂肪的攝取比較低
lower fat intake
脂肪的攝取比較低
low cholesterol
膽固醇就低
less hormones
荷爾蒙就少
Cells are less likely to grow randomly
細胞就比較不容易亂長
So of course nuns don't get breast cancer
所以尼姑當然不得乳癌啊
the same reason
那同樣的道理
So why is breast cancer more and more common now?
那現在為什麼乳癌越來越高
we joke
我們開玩笑講
Because now
因為現在
Everyone grew up eating McDonald's
大家都是吃麥當勞長大的
Traditional oriental food has less fat
傳統東方食物脂肪比較少
Western food is more fatty
西方食物脂肪比較多
Now everyone pays
那現在大家都是收
eat that eat western food
吃那個吃西方食物
under the influence of western food
受西方食物影響的情況之下
Of course the fat is higher
脂肪當然比較高
high cholesterol
膽固醇高
Of course, the cell proliferation is faster
那當然細胞增生就比較快
Therefore, the chances of getting breast cancer will increase
因此得乳癌的機率也就越來越高
So we know without looking at this
所以我們不看這個就曉得說
we often read newspapers
我們常常看報紙
middle school lady
現在國中的女士
Primary school has not yet graduated
國民小學還沒畢業
started puberty
就開始有青春期
That's because everyone is eating western food now
那因為現在大家都是吃西方食物的影響
Relatively speaking
相對而言
breast development
乳房的發育暖潮的發育
development of the uterine lining
子宮內膜的發育
like our grandmothers
就比我們的祖母
was much taller at that time
那個時候高很多
that plus
那再加上
Just mentioned that hormones will promote cell proliferation
剛才提到賀爾蒙就會促使細胞增生
Of course he is now causing breast cancer to be higher and higher
他當然現在導致現在乳癌越來越高
In addition to the effect of this muscle cell food
除了這個施肌胞食物的影響之外
There is another reason
另外還有一個原因
It is a law of economics and education that we teach medical students
就是我們在教醫學生十二的教的一個經科育律
What is the law of economics and education?
那個經科育律是什麼
That is to say, a cell in our body
就是說一顆細胞我們大家身體裡面的
is a cell
是一顆細胞
midlife in terms of cells
中期一生就細胞而言
he only does three things
他只做三件事情
The first thing is called the opposite
第一件事情叫做opposite
assassination of cells
叫做細胞的刺殺
What is cell assassination? That is
什麼叫細胞刺殺?就是說
normal cells when found
正常細胞當發現
when the environment doesn't need it
環境不需要它的時候
It will show a high degree of sentiment and say that it is better to die
它就會發揮高度的情操說乾脆自己死了算
like what?
像什麼?
like our thymocytes
就像是我們的胸腺細胞
We grew up with a thymus as a child without a thymus
我們小時候有胸腺長大沒有胸腺
Why?
為什麼?
Thymocytes are the source of immune cells
胸腺細胞是產生免疫細胞的來源
Normally, our immune cells come from the bone marrow
正常的時候我們免疫細胞是骨髓來的
But when we were just born
可是我們剛剛生下來的時候
Incomplete bone marrow development
骨髓發育不完全啊
When we were young, we depended on thymocytes
小時候的我們要靠胸腺細胞
produce immune cells
產生免疫細胞
But when we grow up
可是我們長大之後
After the bone marrow is fully developed
骨髓發育完全之後
Thymocyte Discovery Says It Doesn't Need It
胸腺細胞發現說不需要它了
I used a high degree of love to say that I am dead
自己發揮高度的情招說我死了算了
So this is a phenomenon of a normal cell
所以這個是一個很正常細胞的一個現象
First
第一個
Cells say a second thing besides the first
細胞除了第一件事情還會說第二件事情
That is to say, it is called cell division
就是說就是叫做細胞的分裂
like we grow up in adolescence
就像我們青春期要長大
One bone cell becomes two
骨頭細胞一個變兩個
Only when two become four can we grow taller
兩個變四個我們才會長高啊
So the second thing is called cell proliferation
因此第二件事情就是叫做細胞增生
what are cancer cells
癌細胞就是什麼
A cancer cell is a cell
癌細胞就是指一個細胞
replicative proliferation too divisive
複製增生太分裂
we just said
我們剛才講
The hormone itself will suddenly kill the excessive cell proliferation
荷爾蒙本身就會猝死細胞過度增生
So we just said
因此我們剛才講
Hormones are what cause, for example
荷爾蒙就是導致譬如說
too much fat in the diet
飲食當中脂肪太多
lead to more hormonal exposure
就會導致荷爾蒙暴露比較多
So the chances of Drew coming are higher.
因此德魯來的機率就比較多
Drew's coming also has something to do with the third thing
德魯來還有跟第三件事情有關
In addition to death, suicide and proliferation of cells
細胞除了死亡自殺增生之外
The third thing is called
第三件事情就是叫做
What is differentiation? A cell does what it is supposed to do
什麼叫分化?一個細胞做它應該做的事情
is called differentiation
就是叫做分化
So we joke about cell division versus cell differentiation
因此我們開玩笑講細胞的分裂跟細胞的分化
A cell will only choose one thing to do again
細胞只會選一件事情來再做
It means that as far as cells are concerned, there is no further study.
等於是說就細胞而言沒有什麼再直進修啊
That is to say, studying at school is studying at school
就是說在學校讀書就是在學校讀書
Play a specific role in social work
在社會工作扮演特定的角色就扮演特定的角色
He can't do two things together
他不會兩件事情一起做細胞不會什麼再直進修
So a very important concept is what is called cell differentiation
那因此一個很重要的概念就是說什麼叫做細胞分化
Cell differentiation means that a cell does what it is supposed to do
細胞分化的意思就是指一個細胞做它應該做的事情
So a very important concept arises
因此一個很重要的概念就產生囉
Since three things or two things will only choose one thing to do
既然三件事情或兩件事情只會選一件事情來做
Thus differentiated cells do not divide
因此分化的細胞就不會分裂
Cells that divide do not differentiate
分裂的細胞就不會分化
That is, assuming a breast cell does what it's supposed to do,
也就是說假設一個乳房細胞做它應該做的事情的話
less likely to get breast cancer
就比較不會得乳癌
I just thought, what are breast cells supposed to do?
我就想 乳房細胞應該做什麼事情
Breast cells are supposed to produce breast milk
乳房細胞應該產生母乳啊
So everyone thinks that the answer to the mystery will be revealed gradually.
因此大家想 謎底逐漸揭曉喔
What kind of opportunity would make a girl
什麼樣的機會會讓一個女生
breast cells that produce breast milk
乳房細胞產生母乳
Pregnant and have a baby
懷孕生小孩啊
Therefore, pregnancy and childbirth is to protect a girl
所以 懷孕生小孩也是保護一個女生
A very important factor in preventing breast cancer
不得乳癌的一個很重要的一個因素
So put it together, the mystery is gradually revealed
因此湊起來 謎底逐漸揭曉
So why are we getting more and more breast cancer now?
那為什麼我們現在乳癌越來越高
On the one hand, Cellfood has more fat and more cholesterol
一方面 細胞食物的影響脂肪多 膽固醇多
Hormones are high, cell proliferation and division are more
荷爾蒙高 細胞增生分裂比較多
Of course, it is getting higher and higher. Two aspects, changes in pregnancy behavior
那當然越來越高 二方面 懷孕型為的改變
Why don't you get married now, get married late, don't have children, have children late
現在大家什麼不結婚 晚結婚 不生小孩 晚生小孩
The number of children is small, and there is no time to replenish milk after giving birth
生小孩 數目又少 生完小孩又沒有時間去補乳
If this natural protective factor is used less and less
這個天生的保護因素越來越不用的話
Of course, she has more chances of splitting
那當然 她的分裂的機會就比較多
Of course, the incidence rate of cancer is relatively high.
癌症發生劇率當然就比較高啊
Therefore, these two reasons fully explain breast cancer
因此這兩大原因就充分的解釋乳癌
happening higher and higher
發生越來越高
A long time ago, three or four years ago, with the Tri-Service General Hospital
在很早之前三四年前就跟三軍總醫院
Vice President Yu Zhicheng said in our cooperation
余志成副院長我們合作說
Since the risk factor you just mentioned
既然你剛才講的危險因子
What is early?
什麼出經早啊
Not pregnant or the first birth is late
不懷孕啊或者是第一胎生態晚啊
or have no breastfeeding experience
或者是沒有補乳的經驗
These factors are really so important
這些因素真的那麼重要
then let's find
那我們來找
Come to find girls in Taiwan after all
來找說到底台灣地區女生
Each of these three risk factors
這三個裡面每多一個危險因素
Doubling the risk of breast cancer
到底會多增加乳癌幾倍的危險性
So 759 patients were recruited at Tri-Service General Hospital
因此就在三軍總醫院找了759位病人
Of course it's not just about seeing patients.
當然不僅要看病人啊
A total of 1,200 healthy girls were found
也要看不得病的一共找了1200位健康的女生
that than what
那比什麼
It's easier than this, one, two, three, what is it?
比這個很簡單比這個一個兩個三個到底是
These patients are no different from healthy people
這些病人跟健康的人到底是0個不好
One is bad, two is bad or three is bad
一個不好兩個不好還是三個不好
Do the statistics and find that
做一下統計的確發現
Breast cancer in Taiwan is indeed related to these three traditional factors
台灣地區乳癌的確跟這個三個傳統的因素
Hormonal factors are highly correlated with pregnancy factors
荷爾蒙的因素懷孕因素高度相關
Because sick people compare with healthy people
因為病人跟健康的人比較
Each additional
每多一個
1.4 to 3 times more likely to develop breast cancer
會多一點四三倍的機率會得乳癌
With this conclusion, we were itching to be healed at the time.
有了這個結論 我們當時癢癢得醫啊
As a result, Dr. Yu told his patients
結果 余大夫喔 跟他的病人講
As a result, immediately filled with frustration, immediately choked by his patient
結果 馬上充滿了挫折感 馬上被他的病人嗆聲
Why do we compare patients to controls—comparing
為什麼 我們比較病人跟對照組一比較起來
Indeed, patients are more likely than controls to have risk factors
的確 病人比對照組更容易有危險因子
But why is it choked up?
可是 為什麼會被嗆聲呢?
look at the patient carefully
你仔細看病人
On the one hand, we acknowledge that these risk factors are important
我們一方面承認這些危險因素很重要
But you really see patients
可是你真的看病人
There are also as high as nearly 40%
也有高達將近40%
What about 39% of patients?
39%的病人是怎麼樣?
Not a single risk factor
一個危險因素都沒有啊
The representative said, are these factors important? Of course they are
代表說 這些因素重不重要? 當然重要
But these factors
可是這些因素
There is no way to explain all that happens in breast cancer
沒有辦法解釋乳癌發生的全部
In fact, this matter is often found abroad
事實上這件事情在國外也常常發現
For example, let me show you
譬如說 我給大家看
A recent study
最近的一篇研究
was made in Europe
是在歐洲做的一個
One of the things he does is called dietary intervention.
他做的一件事情就是叫做飲食的介入
Because we just said that aunts don't get breast cancer
因為我們剛剛講泥姑不得乳癌
So in the European study here
因此在這邊歐洲研究當中
A total of 4690 girls were found
就一共找了4690位女生
The regulations say that you are 2349 people in the control group
規定說你是對照組2349位
2340 people said that eating meat is not good
2340位說那個吃肉不好
start eating vegetarian
你趕快開始吃素
Therefore, there are 2,340 vegetarians and 2,300 in the control group
因此有2340位吃素組2300位是對照組
Observed 16 years to see their lives
觀察到16年來看他們的生命
let's see
讓我們來看
For the control group it happened like this
就對照組而言發生這樣子
Of course, the longer you track, the easier it is to get breast cancer
當然追蹤越久越容易得乳癌
it's useless
這是無用字的
our main concern is
我們最關心的是
What happens to the intervention group equal to the bland food group?
介入組等於是清淡食物組會變成怎麼樣
what's on our mind
我們心裡面想的是什麼
Eating bland food should have no fat
吃清淡食物應該沒有脂肪
It's hard to get breast cancer
很不容易得乳癌
But everyone found
可是大家發現
come and see
你來看
I just found out a few months ago
這是前幾個月才發現
published results
發表的結果
it turns out
竟然
look at their reality
你看他們現實是什麼
The blue ones are on top of the yellow ones in terms of statistics
藍的都在黃的上面統計起來而言
16 years of being a nigga doesn't do any good
當了16年的尼古沒有任何的好處
Relatively speaking, there is a 1.19 times more chance of breastfeeding than the creator
相對而言還比對造主多了1.19倍的機率會的乳完
In fact, this conclusion is not surprising at all.
事實上這個結論一點都不稀奇
This conclusion was called overweight during the most famous medical period in the United States in 2006
這個結論在2006年美國最有名的醫學期間叫做加碼
There has been a larger study
已經有一個更大規模的研究
Harvard University
就是美國的哈佛大學
It tracked 200,000 of that so-called nurse
它一共追蹤了20萬個那個所謂的護士
Because nurses are very supportive of medical research
因為護士對於醫學研究就很支持
Therefore, in the tracking of this 8
因此就是在這個8的追蹤當中
200,000 nurses tracked over 8 years
20萬個護士追蹤了8年當中
We look at the incidence of common cancers
我們看常見癌症的發生率
and the incidence of chronic diseases we're talking about
以及我們講的慢性疾病的發生率
The first is breast cancer
第一個就是乳癌
The black ones refer to the bland food group
黑色的呢就是指清淡食物組
The gray one is generally we joke that it is bigger than the big meat group
灰色的呢就是一般我們開玩笑講大於大肉組
This is what everyone sees
主要大家看的就是這個
Although the bland food group was slightly
雖然清淡食物組比大於大肉組稍微
would for the first point
會為第一點
But doing statistical analysis brings congratulations
可是做統計分析帶來賀禮
What is drawn is superscript and subscript
畫的就是上標跟下標
Considering from the result of superscript
從上標的結果來考慮的話
In fact, there is not much difference between the two
事實上兩者是沒有什麼太大差別
Been a nun for eight years
當了八年的尼姑
In fact, the prevention of breast cancer
事實上對於乳癌的預防
don't contribute at all
一點貢獻都沒有
According to this foreign study
按照這個國外的研究
Let's look at Chinese studies
那我們看華人的研究
is my good friend
就是我的好朋友
That Professor Zheng is there
那個鄭教授在那個
The so-called famous Shanghai
所謂的有名的上海的
Breast Cancer Study
Bress Cancer Study
breast cancer research
乳癌的研究
He is in the Shanghai area
他就是在上海地區
Followed nearly a thousand girls
追蹤了將近幾千個女生
and then depending on their diet
然後依據他們飲食的情態
For example, you see
譬如說大家看到
One, two, three, four is the group of vegetarians
一二三四就是吃素的類組
Instead, he is divided into a little element
他反而分為一點點素
a little more vegetarian
有一點多素
To the last fourth is to be completely vegetarian
到最後第四就是完全吃素
One, two, three, four should be lighter
一二三四應該是越清淡
But look at the incidence of breast cancer
可是你看乳癌的發生率
If the first group is regarded as one
把第一組當作一的話
one point zero one point zero one point zero one point zero
一點零一點零一點零一點零
how is it
是怎麼樣
no help
沒有任何的幫助
Hence this result
因此這個結果
just tell us a frustrating
就告訴我們一個很沮喪的
That is to say, the occurrence of Hollanda is of course closely related to breast cancer.
就是說荷盟的發生當然跟乳癌有很重要的關係
But how much breast cancer does it explain?
可是到底能夠解釋多少乳癌的發生
looks very limited
看起來非常有限
That girl is crazy
那一個女生就很狂恐
Said that you didn't seem to have any risk factors before
說你早之前危險因子看起來都沒有
In terms of public health
從公共衛生的話來講
take extreme precautions
做出極預防
It seems that it is not easy to have a good effect
好像不容易有很好的效果
The public health scientist is like the deputy dean
那公共衛生學家像副院長
He said we started doing stimulus prevention
他就說我們開始做刺激預防
how to stimulate prevention
怎麼刺激預防
Early detection and early treatment
早期發現早期治療嘛
Therefore breast cancer
因此乳癌當中
Girls aged four to five now in the Department of Health
現在衛生署四至五歲的女生
every two years or three years
每兩年還是三年
The government health insurance supplements the payment once
政府健保補給那個給付做一次
so-called mammography
所謂的乳防攝影
Because you said that the food is actually bland
因為你說其實清淡食物
that doesn't do much good
那個沒有什麼太大的好處
Then we have no choice but to retreat to the second line
那我們沒辦法只好退到第二線
with early detection by mammography
用早期發現藉由乳防攝影
for early detection of breast cancer
來早期發現乳癌的發生
Then of course do mammography
那當然要做乳防攝影
psychology itself
本身就要心理
That's very brave, I want to say I'm going to surgery
那個很勇敢啊就想說我要去外科啊
It's troublesome to line up with others
跟人家排隊啊這很麻煩
And that good friend who had a mammogram must know
而且那個做過乳房攝影的那個好朋友一定曉得
It's very, very painful.
這壓起來啊非常非常的痛
Girls can't stand it
女生都是受不了
but no way
可是沒辦法
Striking the bathroom does not work
出擊浴房沒有效
Then we start early detection
那我們就開始早期發現嘛
That benefits Taiwan's advanced medical standards
那得利於現在台灣的醫學水準發達
The one who did the mammography has a lot of doctors who are very good
做乳房攝影的那個很多醫生水準都很高
The main thing in mammography is to catch a little
乳房攝影最主要的是抓一點
the so-called capping point
就是所謂的蓋化點
That is to say, there's still obvious finesse here.
就是說這裡還是很明顯的精精
That is to say, some girls will see a little bit in the middle of the breast
就是說有些女生在乳房當中就會看到一點一點
Gaihua dots like grains of rice
像米粒一樣的蓋化點
For example, the cover point is obvious
譬如說這一點蓋化點就很明顯
or is it
或者是呢
I saw that the so-called Department of Histology was seen on the right hand side
看到說就是大家右手邊看到所謂的組織學系被
Just now this is a normal breast duct.
剛才這上面就是正常的乳管嘛
as we just saw
就我們剛才看過
So the assumption is that the milk ducts are starting to proliferate a little bit normally.
那假設是乳管開始有點正常的增生
There are more and more cells like this
就是這樣的細胞越來越多
Another less favorable situation is called
另外一個比較不好的情形就是叫做
Abnormal hyperplasia is called ADH
異常的增生就是叫做ADH
The difference between here and here is that there are more cells
看到這裡跟這裡的差別就是細胞更多了
therefore
因此
Therefore by mammography
因此藉由乳房攝影
Hoping to find a cover point
希望能夠找到蓋化點
and the circumstances in which this ADH is found
以及找到這種ADH的情形
Because I hope to catch it earlier
因為希望能夠更早期的抓到
Abnormal proliferation of cells
細胞異常增生的情形
If you find a capillary point or an abnormal growth
因為發現蓋化點或者是異常增生的話
It may mean that the breast cells have begun to grow randomly
有可能代表乳腺細胞開始已經亂長了
So the surgeons say it's not good
因此外科醫生都說這個不太好
You should take that cell out and cut it off
你應該把那個細胞拿出來把它切掉
Wow that girl was struggling
哇那時候那個女生就心裡掙扎
Going to that or that official surgery for him to have an operation
要去那個那個官外科他動手術
it hurts him to pull in
他抽進去很痛
I want that wound
還要那個傷口
And that two or three months can not touch the water
還要那個兩三個月不能碰水
And that smoked a piece of meat
而且那個一抽一塊肉
Pull it in and take it out sometimes the breasts will deform
抽進去拿出來有時候乳房會變形
So it's a simple outpatient procedure
所以他是很簡單的一個門診手術
So there is no way
因此可是沒辦法啊
That person talks about that and that Gaihua point
那個人家講說那個那個蓋化點
Or that ADH is a precursor to bisexual breast cells
或者是那個ADH是會變成二性乳房細胞的一個前兆
Therefore, because the screening tools in Taiwan are very developed now
因此因為現在台灣篩檢工具都很發達
So there are a lot of cover points and ADH
所以就很多蓋化點跟ADH
was found that a lot of that that
被找到 那很多那個那個就
women would worry
婦女就會很擔心說
Am I a malignant breast cell?
我到底是不是惡性的乳腺細胞
But really you ask an oncologist
可是真的你問一個腫瘤科醫師
you ask a surgeon
你問一個外科醫師
What are the chances of this changing here?
這裡變到這裡的機率有多少
40 so only 15%
40這樣只有15%
That is to say
也就是說
85% of girls get white cancer after that injection
85%的女生那一針都是白癌了
It's all pain, it's all white pain
都是痛都是白痛了
Because most of the generalized points
因為絕大部分的概化點
ADH
絕大部分的ADH
It's all benign and it doesn't matter.
都是屬於良性的都沒有關係的
So it's hard to retreat to the second line
因此好不容易退到第二線
We hope to find an earlier discovery
我們希望能夠找到一個更早期發現
Indicators of breast cancer such as mammography
乳癌的指標譬如說乳房攝影
But it seems that the result is also
可是看起來結果也是
85% of that and that's irritation prevention is for nothing
85%的那個那個的刺激預防都白做
So from what you said just now that dietary intervention
因此從剛才你說那個飲食介入
eat bland food
要吃清淡食物
Or back off to the second line for mammography
或者是退到第二線再做乳房攝影
Tell us about the spirit mentioned by Dean Zeng Wu just now
告訴我們剛才曾務院長提到那種精神
tell us about the risk factors
告訴我們說危險因素
Very important. These risk factors include light
很重要 這些危險因素包括清淡
That diet eats too much oil
那個飲食吃得太多油
What Covered Points Are Included
包括了什麼蓋化點
these things are important
這些東西都很重要
But these things can't be explained
可是這些東西沒有辦法解釋
all disease occurrences
疾病發生的全部
Even a large proportion of breast cancers occur
甚至有一大部分的乳癌的發生
There is no way to explain it by these traditional factors
沒有辦法藉由這些傳統的因素來解釋
what to do
那怎麼辦
so keep going
那因此就繼續走下去
Not just male breast cancer, but female breast cancer
不僅是男生乳癌 女生乳癌是這樣
Let's look at breast cancer in boys
我們來看男生的乳癌
Liver cancer ranks first among male breast cancers
男生乳癌當中第一名的就是肝癌
The incidence of liver cancer is gradually decreasing
肝癌你看發生率逐漸下降
Why is the incidence of liver cancer gradually decreasing now?
為什麼肝癌現在發生率逐漸下降
Thanks to the famous Professor Bisley
感謝那個有名的畢斯里教授
in 1981
在1981年的時候
He followed a group of more than 20,000 people from Taiwan
他就追蹤一群台灣的2萬多個
turn out
結果發現
b Incidence of liver cancer in the generation of the liver
逼肝的代元的肝癌發生率
During this 15-year track
在這個15年的追蹤當中
Not more than 200 times that of forced liver
不是逼肝的200多倍
Liver Generation
因此就建立起逼肝代元
relationship with liver cancer
跟肝癌發生的關係
In fact, there is another important discovery
事實上還有另外一個重要的發現
It is discovered that this liver B can be vertically transmitted
就是發現這個B肝是可以垂直傳染
Can be passed from mother to child
可以媽媽傳給小孩
Therefore, we can predict that the incidence of liver cancer will gradually decrease after vaccination
所以我們打完疫苗之後可以預見肝癌的發生力會逐漸下降
But why is it still so high?
可是為什麼還會那麼高呢?
At that time, it is worth mentioning a recent study by our Vice President Chen
那時候就值得提到我們陳副院長最近的一篇研究
Except liver B
除了B肝之外
What is another important risk factor for liver cancer?
另外還有一個很重要的肝癌危險因素是什麼?
Hepatitis C
C型肝炎啊
Hepatitis virus A, B, C, D keeps going
肝炎病毒A、B、C、D一直走下去
Beyond Hepatitis B
B型肝炎之外
following a hepatitis C virus
下面一個C型肝炎病毒
It's just a very important event.
也是剛來一個很重要的發生啊
This is a great student of Vice President Chen
這個陳副院長的一個很棒的學生
Dr. Mi Hyun Lee
就是李美玄博士
A study published in the world's most prestigious cancer journal last year
在去年全世界最有名的癌症期刊發表的一篇研究
It’s long-term tracking, how much tracking, and ten years of tracking to see what to say
就是長期追蹤追蹤多少追蹤十年來看說什麼
Hepatitis C very high Hepatitis C very low
C型肝炎很高的 C型肝炎很低的
Hepatitis C undetectable or no hepatitis C at all
C型肝炎測不到的還是根本沒有C型肝炎
divide it into four groups
把它分作四組
you did find
你的確發現
Ten years ago, the group with the highest Qixing Qiannian
在十年之前,七行干年很高的这组
Indeed, compared with the following three groups
的确比下面三组
Ten years after Ganya, the occurrence rate of Ganya is much higher
甘崖十年之后,甘崖的发生率高很多
no doubt
这无庸置疑
tell us again
再一次的告诉我们说
Infection in Qixing Qiannian is Taiwan
七行干年的感染是台湾地区
Ganya is a very important factor
甘崖很重要的因素
But let's look at this picture again
可是我们再来看这个图
the same story happened again
同样的故事又产生了
you said very high
你说很高
is relative to 14.71, relative to 6.4, relative to 1.1
是相对于14.71,相对6.4,相对1.1
High compared to 0.4
相对于0.4很高
but on the other hand
可是另外一方面
Let's say I'm the Great Plainsman of Xigan
假设我是西甘的大原者
I'm afraid to say it when I see this
我看到这里就很怕说
This assumption I am very high
这个假设我是很高的话
then i'm scared
那我就很吓说
Will you get Gan Ya after ten years?
这个十年之后会不会得甘崖
But everyone see
可是大家看
14.1 will also get Gan Ya
14.1也会得甘崖
what the representative said
代表说什么
85% of the high Xigan Dayuan people after ten years
85%的高西甘大原者十年之后
Still won't get Gan Ya
还是不会得甘崖
what are you afraid of
那你怕什么
Most Xigan people will not get Ganya
绝大部分西甘人不会得甘崖
So the story just now came again
因此刚才那故事又来了
Can Xi Gan do it?
西甘做不做得
of course do not do
当然做不做
But can he explain
可是他有沒有辦法解釋
All of the Peerless Diseases
絕世的疾病的全部
can't
不能啊
And peerless
而且絕世
Most people with western liver disease will not get liver cancer
大部分西肝的人不會得肝癌
Just now the story happened again
剛才那故事又產生了
What about the diet?
那你說那飲食啊
these things are not important
這些東西不重要
let's do that
那我們來那個
put these things don't smoke
把這些東西不要抽菸
Don't drink, don't be sick wolf
不要喝酒不要交病狼
Then you say smoking is good?
那你說抽菸好不好
Of course smoking is bad
抽菸當然不好啊
Smoking is four times more likely to get lung cancer than non-smoking
吸菸是不吸菸得肺癌的四倍
Among those 100 lung cancer patients
那100個肺癌的病人當中
There are 80 smokers
有80個的抽菸
so smoking is bad
所以抽菸不好
That's why that Sister Sun Yue asked us to say
所以那個孫月姆姆才叫我們說
Ah, don't smoke
啊都不要抽菸啊
But you ask people to quit smoking
可是你請人家戒菸
what people think
人家心裡面想的
Guess everyone
大家猜猜
100 smokers
100個抽菸的人
In the end, how many people got liver cancer?
到最後得肝癌來幾個
In fact only how much
事實上只有多少
That is to say
也就是說
You tell people to quit smoking
你叫人家戒菸
Why don't people quit smoking
人家幹嘛不要戒菸
Because 85% of people who smoke will not get liver cancer
因為85%的人抽菸不會得肝癌
It's the same story as before
跟剛才的故事都一樣啊
Therefore these things
因此這些東西
fully tell everything
充分的告訴每件事情
occurrence of disease
疾病的發生
Although
雖然
risk factors matter
危險因素很重要
But these risk factors seem to explain only a fraction of the disease
可是這些危險因素似乎只能夠解釋疾病的一點點的部分
It's not just the disease that happens
不僅是疾病發生是這樣子
It's not just cancer
不僅是癌症是這樣子
The same goes for other chronic diseases.
那個其他慢性疾病也是一樣啊
Here you can see that it is the diabetes we are talking about.
這裡給大家看到就是我們講的糖尿病啊
what is diabetes about
糖尿病跟什麼有關
The doctor must have told his patient
那科醫生一定跟他的病人講說
Ah, your medicine doesn't work
啊你吃藥都沒效
what is the best medicine
最好的藥是什麼
lose weight first
先要減重
because
因為
Everyone, what you have seen
各位各位大家看到的
What about the horizontal axis?
橫軸呢
is what we call the obesity index
就是我們講的肥胖指數
square your weight
把你的體重水升高平方
What about the heavy shaft?
重軸呢
It is the percentage of occurrence of diabetes
就是糖尿病的那個發生的百分比
what about blue
藍色的呢
a diabetic patient
就是糖尿病的病人
what about white
白色的呢
just normal
就是一般的
so-called non-diabetic people
所謂不是糖尿病的人
Then just say it
那麼一比就講的說
blue is to the right of white
藍色的是在白色的右邊
It's the blue diabetic patient
就是藍色的糖尿病的病人
his body mass index
他的體位指數
Distribution of the obesity index
肥胖指數的分布
fatter than average
比一般人來的胖
So this is what doctors often say
所以這在那科醫生常常講的說
The best medicine is to lose weight first
最好的藥是先要減重
But now medicine is definitely not saying this
可是現在醫學絕對不是說這個
unimportant
不重要
what medicine sees now
現在醫學看到的是什麼
the following
下面這個
you see blue people
你看藍色的人當中
Some people are also below BMI22.5
有些人也是在BMI22.5以下
that's light
那很輕耶
Why Not Everyone With Diabetes
為什麼並不是所有糖尿病的人
overweight
體重的過重
the same reason
同樣的道理
to ask someone to lose weight
以請人要減重
Why do people want to lose weight?
人家幹嘛要減重
there are a lot of people
有一大堆人
you see white
你看白色的
There are a lot of people whose BMI is above 30 or 35
有一大堆人BMI在30、35以上
But not all overweight people
可是並不是所有體重的過重的人
will get diabetes
都會得到糖尿病
The story just came again
剛才故事又來了
occurrence of disease
疾病的發生
occurrence of lung cancer
肺癌的發生
occurrence of breast cancer
乳癌的發生
occurrence of liver cancer
肝癌的發生
occurrence of diabetes
糖尿病的發生
Tradition matters
傳統因素很重要
But these factors
可是這些因素
Cannot explain all disease occurrences
不能夠解釋疾病發生的全部
let's take a step back
那我們退一步想
disease treatment
疾病治療
For example, for a girl
譬如說對一個女生而言
she started saying
她開始說
will i get
我會不會得
why do you get
為什麼會得
These things were mentioned to you just now
這些東西剛才跟各位提到
what to do after you get it
得了之後怎麼辦
how to treat
要用什麼方法治療
what method to use to be effective
要用什麼方法才有效
Also faced the same problem just now
同樣也面臨剛才同樣的問題
for example
就譬如說
in terms of breast cancer
就乳癌而言
Because this is what I know best
因為這個我最熟
among breast cancer
乳癌當中
I just talked about Hormon himself
就剛才講賀蒙本身
Hormon itself can promote cell proliferation
賀蒙本身就會促使細胞增生啊
Promoting cell proliferation leads to cancer
促使細胞增生就會得癌症啊
How does the hormone promote cell proliferation
那賀蒙怎麼促使細胞增生
It is He Meng, the green part that everyone sees
就是賀蒙就是大家看到這個綠色的部分
There is a hormone receptor on the surface of our Wufang cells
會跟我們五防細胞表面有一個賀蒙接受體
two connected together
兩個接在一起
Hormonal receptors are like a medicine stone hole
賀蒙接受體就像一個藥石孔
Hormon is like a medicine stone
賀蒙就像一個藥石
Once opened, the cells start to grow randomly
一開的話細胞就開始亂長
So there is a medicine
因此有一顆藥
That medicine is a very good medicine
那顆藥就是一種非常好的藥
It's called Tamasifen
就叫做Tamasifen
It can treat a patient with female cancer
它能夠治療一個母癌的病人
how it cures
它怎麼治
Its treatment method is very simple and clear
它治的方法非常的簡單明瞭
it's the medicine
就是它這個藥
I will go with Hormon to grab the Hormon acceptor
會跟賀蒙一起去搶賀蒙接受體
Assuming this receptor is taken away by drug
假設這個接受體給藥搶走了的話
This He Meng will not follow this
這個賀蒙就不會跟這個
This acceptor is connected
這個接受體接在一起
so the cells do not proliferate
所以細胞就不會增生
So here is one way
所以這是一種方法
But what are the disadvantages of using Tamasifen
可是用Tamasifen的壞處是什麼
it's a cheap
它是一個很便宜
medicine with few side effects
副作用很小的藥
But it took two
可是用了兩個
After three years, the infection will become resistant
三年之後就會感染生抗藥性
Even some people start Tamasiva
甚至有些人一開始Tamasiva
it doesn't seem to work
好像沒什麼效果
So that tumor can be said to be
因此那個腫瘤可以就是說
Don't worry, there's another pill now
你放心現在還有另外一顆藥
It's called Lephtharol
就是叫做Lephtharol
This drug goes a different way
這顆藥走的是另外一種方式
In this way, we call it the bird thief and the first bird king
這種方式我們把它稱之為禽賊先禽王
how to say
怎麼講
It is aimed at the girls after the poultry essence
就是針對禽精之後的女生
After Lephtharol is special about what is poultry essence
Lephtharol特別一下什麼叫禽精之後
It's just that warm tides don't produce hormones
就是暖潮不產生荷爾蒙
Warm tides do not produce hormones
暖潮不產生荷爾蒙
It's not that we don't have hormones in our bodies
並不是說我們體內就沒有荷爾蒙
Because we just said that hormones come from fat
因為我們剛剛講荷爾蒙是脂肪來的
So the hormones before the poultry essence
所以禽精之前的荷爾蒙
will accumulate in our adipose tissue
就會累積在我們的脂肪組織
Once the poultry essence, these past accumulated
一旦禽精之後這些過去累積的
is released by an enzyme
就會釋放出來藉由一個酵素
That enzyme is called Aromatase
那個酵素就是叫做Aromatase
will put past poultry essence before
就會把過去禽精之前
The accumulated hormones are affected by Aromatase
所累積的荷爾蒙藉由Aromatase的作用
It will be converted into hormonal bird essence and then used
就會把它轉換變成荷爾蒙禽精之後來用
That is the pharmacological mechanism of creating this medicine
那在創作這顆藥的藥理機轉
It is to give this converted enzyme to
就是把這個轉換的酵素給
block him
給他阻斷
Of course that's what I just said
那當然就是我剛剛講的
Qin thief pre-Qin king
秦賊先秦王
After putting the whole Pingjin, the source of Horrer Horrer
把整個平津之後賀爾賀爾的來源
After blocking
都阻斷了之後
Of course the hormones are less
那當然賀爾蒙變少
cells will not rot
細胞不會爛斬
Then of course the cancer can be controlled
那當然癌症就可以得到控制
Then you have to use Qin thief and Qin king's trick
那說你要用秦賊又秦王這招
Or use the trick of grabbing the position
還是用那個搶位置這招
According to our common sense
從我們的常理來講
It should be more effective
應該是這一招比較有效
Because it was blocked from the beginning
因為開始就把這裡都阻斷住了
Because here is still going to grab
因為這裡還去搶
sometimes win sometimes lose
有時候搶贏有時候搶輸
But here is the source of fundamental hormones
可是這裡是根本賀爾蒙的來源
After blocking
都阻斷之後
Of course it's less likely to get breast cancer
那當然就比較不容易得乳癌
real
真的
Indeed, judging from the five-year clinical trials conducted in the United States
的確從美國所進行的五年臨床實驗來看的話
This is the incidence of breast cancer
這是乳癌的發生率
after another year
再過了年之後
In the Tamasibon group just now
在剛才Tamasibon這組
just now
就是剛才的
The one who grabbed the position in this group
那個搶位置這組的
The breast cancer recurrence rate is
那個乳癌復發率是
That 13.6%
那個13.6%
But the group of Qin bandits before the king of Qin is 10.3%
可是秦賊先秦王這組是10.3%
Indeed, the group of Qin bandits and pre-Qin kings is more effective
的確秦賊先秦王這組比較有效
But you ask a patient and a surgeon
可是你問一個病人問一個外科醫生
he just said
他就講
Does train meat work?
列車肉有沒有效
Of course it works
當然有效啊
in October 2009
在2009年10月
start health insurance
就開始健保會給付
But train meat has a lot of sequelae
可是列車肉有一大堆後遺症
why
為什麼呢
That's what a lot of older girls want
就是很多那個年長一點的女生就想的
girls get sick
女生會得一種病
called menopause
叫做停經
how is it
怎麼樣呢
Hormones are a good thing.
荷爾蒙本身還是一件好東西啊
Hormones regulate body temperature
荷爾蒙有調節體溫中樞
Hormones prevent bone transport
荷爾蒙有預防骨質輸送
so some girls
因此有一些女生
after her menopause
她停經之後
Just after the warm tide stopped giving birth
就是暖潮不產之後
after menopause
停經之後
flushing throughout the day
整天面部潮紅
I feel that face is dirty all day long, as if I have a fever
整天就感覺到那個臉臟好像發燒一樣
Then there will be bone transport
然後會有骨質輸送
Then you use an artificial way now
那你現在用人為的方式
Block this too
把這個也都阻斷掉了
The source of the hormone is not
那荷爾蒙來源沒有
Of course after menopause
那當然停經之後
It's serious
情就很嚴重啊
So after the train meat is used
因此列車肉用了之後
My good friend from Chang Gung Hospital
我的那個長庚醫院的好朋友
Director Chen Xinshe said
就是陳信社主任他就說
what joint pain
什麼關節痠痛啊
bone transport
骨質輸送啊
Flushing
潮紅啊
Tired
疲勞啊
headache side effects
頭痛的副作用
will make many patients
會讓很多病人都
Can’t bear it, it’s just a serious stop and stop task group.
受不了 就是很嚴重的停停任務群就產生
What to do then he said please bear with me
那怎麼辦 那他就說 請你忍一忍
Unfortunately, Zeng Qingshe is a boy.
那很不幸的 曾慶設是男生啊
Didn't he know just now that you can't work, stop the task group?
他剛剛不是曉得說 你行不通停停任務群
what a pain
多麼樣的痛苦啊
So the same reasoning comes
因此同樣的道理就來了
what about that girl
那一個女生怎麼辦
It's better to choose one
要選一個比較好
but more side effects
可是比較有副作用的藥
or choose a comparison
還是選一個比較
not so good
沒有那麼好
medicine with less side effects
可是副作用比較小的藥
This is also a problem
這個同樣的也是面臨的一個問題
same treatment strategy
同樣的治療策略
But every choice
可是每一個選擇
It seems that there is no fixed answer
都好像沒有一個固定的答案
I just talked about TOMASKIN
剛才講TOMASKIN
It doesn't matter if the super meat is effective
那超肉那個吃有效還沒不打緊
some medicine
有些藥
This is my exaggerated report in 2005
這是我拿2005年比較誇張的報導
That is, there is a doctor at National Taiwan University Hospital who said
就是台大醫院有一個醫生就是說
We have high cholesterol now
我們現在膽固醇都很高
But what?
可是呢
The so-called lipid-lowering drugs we take
我們吃的所謂的降血脂的藥
100% take basic medicine
百分之吃基礎的藥
Everything you eat is free
吃的都是白吃的
It's useless to eat everything
都吃的都沒效的
Just now you said that the super meat is still effective.
剛才你說那超肉還有效還沒關係
Some medicines have no effect at all
有些藥吃的還根本一點效果都沒有
That didn't work at all. It doesn't matter.
那一點效果都沒有 還不打緊
what's more serious
更嚴重的是什麼
There will be drug damage
還會產生藥害啊
Some medicines can also cause serious
有些藥還會產生很嚴重的
that allergic reaction
那個過敏反應啊
Our Department of Health has a foundation
我們衛生署有一個那個基金會
It's called that medicine, that relief.
就是叫做那個藥品那個救濟
the Drug Injury Relief Committee
那個藥害救濟委員會
After counting
統計了之後
8 From 1999 when he founded to 2011
8從1999年他成立到2011年
A total of 705 successfully appealed cases
一共有705個申訴成功的案子
Among them, the first place is 305
其中第一名305位
It's the famous Steven Johnson
就是有名的Steven Johnson
Stevenson Johnson
史蒂文生強生症
It's a severe skin allergy.
他是一個很嚴重的皮膚過敏反應啊
it's the skin like a burn
就是皮膚就像燒傷
The whole skin turns up like this
整個皮膚就這樣翻起來
The skin we are talking about has a normal protective function
那我們講的皮膚有正常的那個保護功能
If you must turn it up
一定要翻起來的話
It's easy to get infected
很容易感染嘛
The drug rash that covered the whole body
起皮全身長滿的那個那個藥物疹
So what medicine should I take
因此到底應該吃什麼藥
Some medicines work and some medicines don't
有些藥有效有些藥沒效
drugs that don't work sometimes
沒效的藥有時候
can also cause severe allergic reactions
還會引起很嚴重的過敏反應
what to do
那怎麼辦
Therefore these things
因此這些東西
Now is the problem that medicine is facing now
現在是現在醫學所碰到的問題
from the beginning we just said
從開始我們剛剛講
Can a nun get breast cancer?
尼姑會不會得乳癌啊
Tell us that privacy is important
告訴我們說隱私很重要啊
But privacy can't explain the whole of the decision.
可是隱私又不能夠解釋決定的全部啊
occurrence of disease
疾病的發生
disease progression
疾病的進展
disease treatment
疾病的治療
full of differences from person to person
充滿人跟人的差異
those factors are important
那些因素都很重要
However, these factors do not seem to be able to explain
可是這些因素似乎不能夠解釋
all diseases
疾病的全部
So we physicians say
因此我們醫學家就說
Then can we tailor-made
那我們能不能量身訂做
like a tailor
就像一個裁縫式一樣
Of course we are now ours
我們當然現在我們的那個
When you go shopping for clothes, there are
去買衣服的時候都是有
small has medium, has s, has m, has l
small 有medium 有s 有m 有l
It's us who come to match the look of this dress
是我們人來符合這個衣服的樣子
that's that
那可是那個
That rich man they don't go with everyone
那個有錢人他們才不跟大家一起去
Which department store buys m or l
那個百貨公司買什麼m還是l
he will ask a tailor to come to his house
他會請裁縫式去他家
Tailored for him
為他量身訂做
according to his figure
依據他的身材
Sin fits him and don't fit m and won't divide into l
罪符合他也不要符合m也不會分成l
He only needs the medicine that suits his figure
他只要符合他身材的那個藥
Thus the concept of personalized medicine was born
因此個人化醫學的概念就產生了
That's what I just said
就是剛才講說那個
that privacy is important
那個隱私很重要
But can't explain the disease
可是不能夠解釋疾病
Is the overall progression of the disease critical?
疾病的全部 進展有快危嗎
What kind of medicine to take? Will the treatment have any side effects?
要吃什麼藥 那治療會不會有副作用
Then can we adapt to each person's different situation?
那我們能不能依據每一個人不同的狀況
Tailored for him
為他量身訂做
The best strategy for the treatment of disease progression
他疾病發生進展治療最好的策略
So that's what we're going to tell you tonight
因此 這就是我們今天晚上要跟大家講的
Personalized medicine is based on the individual
個人化醫學就是以個人為基礎
disease prevention or treatment
疾病的預防或者是治療的方法
In other words, as far as it is concerned, it is called prescribing the right medicine
也就是說 就現在而言就是叫做對症下藥
Prescribe the right medicine, okay?
對症下藥好不好
Of course yes, for the same disease
當然好啊 給同樣的病
Giving the same medicine is what we have in mind
給同樣的藥 是我們心裡面想的
In this medicine, the vast majority of people are effective
在這顆藥 絕大部分人都有效
But some people have no effect
可是 有一些人吃了沒效
Some people even seriously hear the sound of death
有些人甚至還會得很嚴重的死地聞聲強真正啊
Well, personalized medicine is just like that.
那 個人化醫學就 那這樣子不行
We want to be able to drug people
我們希望能夠對人下藥
It is equal to consider that people are different from each other
等於是先考慮到人跟人的不一樣
Why are people different? Vice President Chen just said
怎麼樣人跟人不一樣 陳副院長剛剛講
It's not the same as physique
沒跟體質不一樣啊
Some people are expensive to smoke
有些人吃抽菸會得貴
Some people will not be expensive if they smoke for a lifetime
有些人抽一輩子人不會得貴
Can each person's physical factors be considered first?
能不能先把每一個人的體質因素考慮進來
Then, after taking physical factors into consideration
然後再把體質因素考慮進來之後
decide later
再來決定
It is established that progression is the best strategy for treatment
它既定發生進展治療最好的策略
what is physique
那什麼叫做體質
it's genetic
它就基因啊
It's where people are different
就是人跟人不一樣的地方
Consider each person's genetic status
考慮每一個人基因的狀況
to decide who should eat
來決定說誰應該吃
Who should take this medicine
這顆藥還是誰應該吃
that medicine
那顆藥
So this is the concept of so-called personalized medicine
因此這個就是所謂的個人化醫學的概念
From prescribing the right medicine to prescribing people
從對症下藥到對人下藥
Treatment for disease progression
對於疾病的發生進展治療
make better predictions
做更好的預測
So you've all learned about genetics before
因此大家以前都學過基因
We all know what a gene is
都曉得說什麼是基因
Of course I'm the one here
當然我這裡就是那個
That class is doing a lot of work.
那個班門弄斧一番啊
what is gene
什麼是基因
Genes are in our body
基因就是我們身體裡面
The ruler of any life center
任何生命中樞的主宰啊
inside our body
我們身體裡面
Let's look at the following
我們先看下面
inside everyone's body
每一個人身體裡面
It is composed of individual cells
就是一顆一顆的細胞組成
The composition of everyone is the same
所組成大家都一樣
So our body is like a house
因此我們身體就像一個房子一樣
our house
我們這個房子
is a maximum of ten trillion cells in a house
是最多房子裡面有十兆的細胞
Every cell is constantly being renewed
每一顆細胞都不斷的在更新
What is the master in the cell?
那細胞裡面的主宰是什麼
inside each of our cells
我們的每一顆細胞裡面
where a commander in chief lives
有一個總司令住的地方
the president's house
總統住的家
That place is called the cell box
那個地方就是叫做細胞盒
you take out the cell box
你把細胞盒拿出來
It's what we learned in middle school biology
就是我們國中生物所學的那個東西
are called chromosomes
就是叫做染色體
What are chromosomes?
那什麼叫做染色體呢
we used to carry
以前我們背過
We humans have 23 pairs of chromosomes
我們人有23對染色體
every cell is the same
每個細胞都一樣
Of the 23 pairs of chromosomes
那23對染色體當中
half from dad
一半是爸爸來的
half from mom
一半是媽媽來的
Chromosomes are like balls of yarn
染色體就像毛線球
Once you pull the yarn inside the yarn ball
你把毛線球裡面的毛線是一旦拉開
That's what high school students learn now
就是現在高中學生所學的
It's what we call genes
就是我們講的基因
That's what we call DNA
那個就是我們講的DNA
why
為什麼呢
In our 23 pairs of chromosomes
在我們23對染色體
It is among the 46 balls of yarn
就是46球毛線球當中
There are 30,000 genes in total
一共有3萬個基因
There are 3 billion nuclei
有3十億核核核酸
how to say this sentence
這句話怎麼講
What is 30,000 genes
什麼叫做3萬個基因
Then I am also a tiger.
那我同樣也是斑門弄虎啊
that is
就是說
in our body
在我們身體裡面
The achievement of any physiological phenomenon is protein
任何生理現象的達成都是蛋白質
Proteins that fight on the front lines, such as
前線打仗的蛋白質,譬如說
I see a dog wants to pet me, I want to run faster
我看到一隻狗要養我,我要跑快一點
How can I run faster? My kidneys
我怎麼跑快一點?我的腎臟
My kidneys are pumping out adrenaline
我的腎臟要分泌腎上腺素
contract my muscles
讓我的肌肉收縮
let me run faster
讓我就可以跑快一點
So adrenaline is a protein
因此腎上腺素是一種蛋白質
or the one just now
或者剛才那個
That stuff is delicious, my stomach is going to produce acid
那個東西很好吃,我胃臟要產生胃酸
Stomach acid is also a protein
胃酸也是一個蛋白質
The achievement of any physiological phenomenon depends on
任何生理現象的達成都是靠
protein to do
蛋白質來做
But
可是
People who fight on the front line don't always obey orders
前線打仗的人並不是總吃令
What is the total eating order? What I just said
總吃令是什麼?剛才講的
A cell inside a cell and a ball of yarn inside
細胞裡面的細胞和裡面的毛線球
DNA inside
裡面的DNA
Why? Because we often say a word
為什麼呢?因為我們常常講一句話
It is now that junior high school students start
就是現在國中學生開始
Recite that sentence, what DNA does
背的那句話,什麼DNA做
RNA makes protein, protein expresses function
RNA做蛋白質、蛋白質表現功能
why? because
為什麼呢?因為
total food order in the body
身體裡面的總吃令
will be based on the present
就會依據現在
I saw a dog wanting to pet me, so
我看到一隻狗要養我,因此
The DNA that makes adrenaline turns on
做腎上腺素的那個DNA就打開
DNA to itself
DNA以自己
as a template
當作模板
make a message
做一段傳遞訊息
Let's look at it with a simple diagram
我們用簡單的圖來看
DNA imitates in its own message
DNA以自己訊息當中模仿
Make a simple piece of RNA
做一段簡單的RNA
RNA will help DNA help the general order
RNA就幫DNA幫總支令
pass as orderly
傳遞當傳令兵
to whom
傳給誰
outside the nucleus
傳到細胞核的外面
that is
就是說
Now it's an adrenaline rush
現在要做的是一個腎上腺素
so you want the adrenaline-producing protein
所以你要產生腎上腺素的蛋白質
How to do it
怎麼做
how to do it here
這裡怎麼做到這裡的
It is also what our children in junior high school started to learn.
同樣也是我們現在國中的小朋友開始學的
It turned out that this RNA was sent out
原來送出來這一條RNA
use yourself as a template
就以自己來當作模板
to catch different amino acids
來抓不同的胺基酸
so take care of that
因此管你那個
eat the night before
前一天晚上吃
one thousand three hundred dollars
一千三塊一千三百塊錢的
number of steaks
台數牛排
It's still five yuan for breakfast
還是早上吃五塊錢的
Nucleated eggs are useless
核包蛋都沒用
eat into our stomachs
吃到我們肚子
we'll put thirteen hundred dollars
我們會把一千三百塊錢的
A few steaks or five dollars
台數牛排或者是五塊錢的
the protein in that nucleated egg
那個核包蛋裡面的蛋白質
Amino acids cut one by one
切成一個一個的胺基酸
that one amino acid
那一個一個胺基酸
will be based on
就會依據
This RNA series
這一條RNA的系列
call over
叫過來
therefore
因此
DNA is different
DNA不一樣
RNA is different
RNA就不一樣
The amino acid called is different
叫過來的胺基酸就不一樣
Amino acids are different
胺基酸不一樣
The protein produced is different
做出來的蛋白質就不一樣
therefore
因此
you see the dog keeps biting you
你看到一直狗咬你
you opened
你打開的是
adrenaline gene
腎上腺素的基因
made out of adrenaline
做出來的是腎上腺素
You see that delicious food now
你現在看到那個好吃的食物
You're turning on the gene for stomach acid
你打開的是胃酸的基因
It is made of gastric acid, the protein
做出來就是胃酸這個蛋白質
This is the basics that middle school students are starting to learn now
這是基本的現在國中學生開始學的
Fundamental
基本原理
Then tell me what we just said
那你說跟剛才我們講的
More humane liquid difference
更人化液體差
where is the importance
重要性在哪裡
because
因為
everyone is human
大家都是人
people are the same
人跟人都一樣
But
可是
This one actually has a meringue
這種一樣事實上有個蛋酥
what is that meringue
那個蛋酥是什麼
The DNA in our 46 balls of yarn
在我們那個46球毛線球當中的那個DNA
99.9% the same
有99.9%一樣
almost everyone the same
幾乎大家都一樣
Then you say it's so strange
那你說那有什麼稀奇
Oddly enough
稀奇的是
Didn't we just talk
我們剛才不是講說
The DNA in our body
我們身體裡面這些DNA
There are 3 billion editing teams
有30億隊的剪輯隊
you put
你把
3 billion times the remaining 0.1%
30億乘以剩下的這個0.1%
so what
那就怎麼樣
very big
很大啊
3 billion multiplied by 0.1% is what
30億乘以0.1%就是什麼
3000000
300萬
What will become of this 3 million
這300萬就會變成什麼
The 3 million decided to say
這300萬就決定說
We all have hair genes
大家都有頭髮的基因
But some people have straight hair
可是有人是直頭髮
someone has curly hair
有人是捲頭髮
everyone has that
大家都有那個
eye genes
眼睛的基因
But some people are slit-eyed
可是有些人是單縫眼
some people's eyes just look
有些人眼睛就看起來
That round one doesn't look very pretty
那個圓圓的看起來不怎麼漂亮
Everyone has face genes
大家都有面容的基因
But some people can make idol stars look handsome
可是有些人可以讓偶像明星長得很帥
But some people look like me and look very ordinary
可是有些人像我就長得很普通
so these things
所以這些東西
Although this is 3 billion
這雖然30億裡面
Although in our genes
雖然我們的基因當中
percent
百分之
everyone is the same
大家人都人都一樣
This 99.2% is 900 million
這99.2%就有9億
But this little 0.1%
可是這個小小的0.1%
You multiply 3 billion by 3 million
你把30億一乘的300萬
It is decided that people are different from people
就決定人跟人不一樣
These people are different
這些人跟人不一樣
as usual some people are taller
照常說有些人高
some people are short
有些人矮
some people are handsome
有些人帥
some people are ordinary
有些人普通
some people have straight hair
有些人是直頭髮
some people have curly hair
有些人捲頭髮
Some people who smoke make them shorter
有些人抽煙會得會矮
some people
有些人
I will regret not smoking
不抽菸也會得悔
Some people are allergic to medicine
有些人吃藥會過敏
Some people take medicine without allergies
有些人吃藥不會過敏
Therefore, the current medical research
因此現在醫學研究的
just want to study this
就是希望研究這個
3 billion times zero percent
30億乘以百分之零點
The nucleotide sequence of the 3 million
這300萬個的那個核乾酸的序列
how to explain
到底來如何來解釋
How to decide the development and treatment of the disease
如何來決定疾病的發生進展治療
What's more, many genetic mutations
更何況很多基因的變異
or the day after tomorrow
還是後天所造成的
So this is what we have in mind
因此這個就是我們心裡面想的
personalized medicine
個人化醫學
That humanized medicine is just mentioned
那個人化醫學就是剛才提到的
We hope to take advantage of the fact that people are different from others
我們希望利用這種人跟人的不一樣
to explain disease
來解釋疾病的發生
disease progression disease treatment
疾病的進展 疾病的治療
By taking this into consideration
藉由這點來考慮到
Differences in each person's physique
每個人體質的差異
Impact of treatment on progression
對於發生進展治療影響
In fact, this concept has long been
事實上這個概念很早以前就有
It was in 2001 AD
就是在公元2001年
After the so-called genetic decoding
所謂的基因解碼之後
These 3 billion nucleotides
這30億個核乾酸
After understanding how it is arranged in order
了解它怎麼排列順序之後
everyone is full of fantasy
大家都充滿了幻想
that is, can we
就是說我們能不能
Explain that by 0.1 percent of the three billion
解釋藉由這個三十億當中的百分之零點一
Let's take a look at these treatments for the progression of the disease
來看說到底這些對於疾病的發生進展治療
what kind of impact
到底有什麼樣的影響
that's unfortunate
那很不幸的
Over the past ten years or so, our efforts have not been enough.
這十年多來這個也是我們努力不夠啊
It seems that the explanation is still very limited.
看起來能解釋的還是很有限
a few months ago this year
在今年前幾個月前
We are in that biomedicine
我們在那個生物醫學當中
The most famous journal is called cell
最有名的期刊就是叫做 cell
It means you and us scientists are not working hard enough
它就是說你們我們科學家都不夠努力
what we hope
我們希望的是什麼
It is called genomic reach to the clinic
就是叫做 genomic reach to the clinic
That is to say, can the study of the genome be used in
就是說基因體的研究到底能不能用在
clinic is clinical
clinic就是臨床
it talks and talks
它講來想去有說
only two so far
到目前為止只有兩個
Only two examples in the last year or two
在最近這一兩年內只有兩個例子
what is the first example
第一個例子是什麼
The first example is the treatment of skin cancer
第一個例子就是皮膚癌的治療
Just talking about a drug for skin cancer
就在講皮膚癌的一種藥
Then this drug is based on the assumption that there is no genetic allergy
那這種藥就是假設有沒有基因過敏
may decide which one it is
也許可以決定它哪一種
It's not surprising that we see this
我們看這個不稀奇
In fact, we have more famous examples in Taiwan
事實上我們台灣有更有名的例子
It's the broadcast that you often hear on your mobile phone
就是大家常常在手機上聽到的廣播
just to do
就是要做
Targeted therapy for lung cancer
肺癌的標靶治療
The medicine he talked about is called
他講的這顆藥就是叫做
It's called L-Resa Dark Heat Sha
叫做L-Resa 暗熱痧
Because Taiwan was long ago
因為台灣很早之前
Professor Yang Banshi from National Taiwan University Hospital
像台大醫院的楊半恥教授
they joined long ago
他們很早之前就加入了
International long-term follow-up study
國際的長期追蹤研究
just found one thing
就發現一件事情
That is to say, all lung cancer patients
就是說所有的肺癌病人
can be based on one is called
可以依據一個就是叫做
EGFR is what you hear on the radio
EGFR 就是大家在收音機所聽到的
performance factor
就是叫做表現因子
Is the receptor mutated?
受體有沒有突變
seems to decide
好像可以決定
Who should use it?
到底誰應不應該用
What does Ivresa say?
Ivresa 怎麼講
Everyone look at the upper right corner
大家看右上角
The upper right corner is called EGFR
右上角就是屬於叫做EGFR
mutant group words
突變組的話
The horizontal axis is tracking
橫軸就是追蹤
4 months 8 months 12 months 16 months
4個月 8個月 12個月 16個月
The vertical axis is the patient's survival rate
縱軸就是病人的存活率
What about the gray group?
你看灰色這組呢
The gray group is to eat
灰色這組就是吃
Irresa's group
Irresa 那組
The black group is general chemotherapy
黑色這組就是一般的化療
You can discover the hypothesis
你可以發現假設
EGFR is mutated
EGFR是突變化
sorry i said it the other way around
對不起我講反過來了
The survival rate of eating ERESA is much higher than that of not eating ERESA
吃ERESA比不吃ERESA存活率高很多
On the contrary, the assumption is that EGFR is good for pigs and sheep to change color
反之假設是EGFR是好的豬羊變色
So now a very important personalization
因此現在就一個很重要的個人化
some concepts arise
一些概念就產生了
lung cancer is scary
肺癌很可怕
Lung cancer can only be treated with general chemotherapy
肺癌一般都只能夠用一般的化療
Chemotherapy is very large and not necessarily effective
化療附中很大而且不一定有效
Can that be based on a specific
那能不能依據特定的
Advertisement for treatment, this is the so-called advertised treatment.
的標榜來進行治療這個就是所謂標榜治療啊
ERESA is a good example
ERESA就是一個很好的一個例子
But he said ERESA is not available for everyone
可是他說ERESA也並不是每一個人都可以用
Because the condition of EGFR should be considered if it is assumed that it is a person with a mutation
因為應該考慮到EGFR的狀況假設是突變的人的話
Is ERESA valid
是ERESA有效
People who are not mutants are ERESA ineffective
不是突變的人是ERESA沒效
What is EGFR?
什麼是EGFR呢
EGFR is what we just said that there is an electric spirit on the surface of every cell
EGFR就是我們剛剛講每一顆細胞表面都有一個電靈
This electric spirit is one that receives messages from the outside world.
這個電靈就是接受外界訊息的一個
main receptor
主要的受體
So what is the main role of this electric spirit?
那這個電靈主要的角色是什麼
outer cells say
外面細胞有說
If it takes longer, the electric spirit will notify the commander-in-chief in the cells and pancreas to say
要長的話 電靈就會通知細胞和胰裡面的總司令說
please grow up
請你趕快長
Therefore, many patients with lung cancer just said
因此有很多肺癌的病人剛才講
Assuming that EGFR is a mutation
假設是EGFR是屬於突變的話
what is this patient
這種病人等於是什麼
His electric spirit can't play when pressed
他的電靈按下去就彈不起來
Just as the false biography of the holy will said, hurry up and grow
就在假傳聖誌說 趕快長
RESA is the drug that blocks the electric spirit
RESA這顆藥就是會阻斷電靈
The process of passing on the whole message
把整個訊息傳下去的過程
Therefore, if EGFR is assumed to be broken
因此EGFR假設壞掉的話
is RESA valid
是RESA有效
EGFR is supposed to be that normal
EGFR假設是那個正常的話
It's the RESA that doesn't work
是那個RESA就沒效
So this is a very successful
所以這個就是一個很成功的
The concept of personalized medicine
個人化醫學的概念
For the treatment of lung cancer
對於肺癌的治療而言
Taking into account the fact that a person is genetically different
考慮到一個人基因不同的情況
Is it EGFR positive?
到底是EGFR陽性
Still EGFR negative
還是EGFR陰性
positive give this medicine
陽性給這個藥
Negative do not give this medicine
陰性不給這個藥
can determine each patient's season
可就能夠決定每個病人的季後
as far as our breast cancer is concerned
就我們乳癌而言
It is also related to this EGFR
同樣也是跟這個EGFR有關
EGFR has a relative
EGFR有一個親戚
The other name is called
那另外一個名稱就是叫做
Another relative of EGF in breast cancer is
乳癌當中另外一個EGF的親戚就是
burn
HR2
What is HR2 the same as EGF just now
HR2是什麼跟剛才EGF一樣
It is also the electric spirit on the surface of the cell membrane.
也是細胞膜表面的電靈
That's an example of long-term tracking
那這是長期追蹤的例子
base it on what was just said
把它依據剛才講的
Hormone receptors are just mentioned
荷爾蒙的受體就是剛才講的
see the ER
看到的ER
Or whether HR2 is positive or negative
或者是HR2到底是陽性跟陰性
Break it down into these groups
把它拆成這幾組
You can find that the worst group is the green group
你可以發現最差的這一組就是綠色這一組
The horizontal axis is tracking years
橫軸就是追蹤幾年
The main axis is the patient's survival rate
重軸就是病人的存活率
You can find out who the green group is
你可以發現綠色這一組是誰
The green group is HR2 positive
綠色這一組就是HR2陽性的
Even if Dianling presses the button, it can't be squeezed out.
就是電靈按下機都擠不來的
So is it possible to consider a person
因此能不能夠考慮到一個人
HR2 status to give specific drugs
HR2的狀況來給特定的藥
Just like considering the status of a person's EGF
就像剛才考慮一個人EGF的狀況
To consider whether he can give ERSR
來考慮說他是不是能夠給ERSR
Of course the most famous example of breast cancer is this
當然乳癌最有名的例子就是這個
Just check the status of that HR2 first
就是先檢查那個HR2的狀況
Now the health insurance bureau is saying
就是現在健保局就擠富說
Suppose to check that HR2 first
假設先檢查那個HR2
what is this thing
這個東西是什麼
This thing is to see a patient
這個東西就是去看說一個病人
Or look at each cell of you and me
或者是看你跟我每一個的細胞
Is the Horn Rabbit over-acting?
到底荷爾兔有沒有過度表現
Assuming that the Horn rabbit is normal, it should be
假設荷爾兔正常的話應該是
The Horn Rabbit given by Dad The Horn Rabbit given by Mom
爸爸給的荷爾兔 媽媽給的荷爾兔
There should only be two red dots
應該只有兩個紅點
But look at this cancer cell
可是你看這個癌症細胞
Horror rabbits have so many points like this cell
荷爾兔像這顆細胞有那麼多點
On behalf of the volume of the Horn rabbit has changed a lot
代表荷爾兔的量變很多
The volume of Hole rabbits has changed a lot, and the power has changed several times
荷爾兔的量變很多 電力變好幾個
Of course the cells keep growing
那當然細胞就不斷的生長
So the NHS says
因此健保局就說
Assume that the patient is a Holle rabbit
假設這個病人是屬於荷爾兔
If it belongs to more than two planes
是屬於兩架以上的話
then specific medicines can be given
那就可以給特定的藥
Not only to see if this Horn rabbit is over-performing
不僅是看這個荷爾兔有沒有過度表現
Sometimes to stain the protein of the Horn rabbit
有時候去染荷爾兔的蛋白質
When the protein is dyed, it becomes brown
蛋白質染出來就咖啡色
You see this is what we say
你看這個就是我們說
The position of the Horn rabbit is outside the cell
那個荷爾兔的位置就是在細胞的外面
your outside is brown brown
你的外面都咖啡色咖啡色
What about normal cells?
那正常細胞呢
Normal cells should not be so concentrated
正常細胞應該不是那麼濃
But some patients are so strong
可是有些病人荷爾兔就是那麼樣的強
So for breast cancer
因此對乳癌而言
Horror Rabbit Positive vs. Horror Rabbit Negative
荷爾兔陽性相對荷爾兔陰性
Hordu-positive people have particularly poor survival
荷爾杜陽性的人存活力特別差
Can it be the same as the IRA killing against the DGA just now?
能不能就像剛才IRA殺來針對DGA把一樣
Is there any special medicine for Hordu?
荷爾杜有沒有特別的藥呢
Because if it is assumed to be Hordu positive
因為假設是荷爾杜陽性的話
If it is known in advance that the patient is Hordu positive
假設事先曉得說這個病人是屬於荷爾杜陽性的話
That should give him special medicine.
那應該對他給他特別的藥啊
Indeed, health insurance pays for a drug
的確健保就給付一種藥
It is Hercetin hormone cancer bottle
就是Hercetin 荷爾癌瓶
That is, assuming the surgical findings say
就是說假設外科手術發現說
if hordu overacts
荷爾杜有過度表現的話
you can give him a hormone cancer bottle
就可以給他荷爾癌瓶
then at most one year
然後頂多給一年
give him 13 times a year
一年給他13次
He said why is the NHS so stingy?
他說健保局為什麼那麼小氣
So personalization together with another concept was born
因此個人化一起另外一個概念就產生了
We're all talking about targeted therapy now
我們現在都在講標靶治療
They say I should drug people
都在講我應該對人下藥
Instead of just prescribing the right medicine
而不應該只是對症下藥
Shouldn't all be just the usual chemotherapy drugs
不應該都只是給一般的化療藥
It should be seen whether each person is
應該看每一個人到底是
Hercetin Hordu positive
Hercetin 荷爾杜陽性
Assuming Hercetin Hordu positive
假設是Hercetin 荷爾杜陽性的話
Just give him a cancer hormone bottle, a cancer hormone bottle
就給他荷爾癌瓶 荷爾癌瓶
There are special medicines for Hordu positive
荷爾杜陽性特別有藥
But why is the NHS so bright and stingy?
可是為什麼健保局那麼亮的小氣
Because of Hordu
因為荷爾杜一管
More than 60,000 yuan is a year
六萬多塊錢是一年
Health insurance will pay 800,000
健保就要給付80萬
Therefore, the National Health Insurance Bureau did not dare to open
所以以前健保局不敢開放
Hersetting is the first medication
hersetting是第一件用藥
Later passed by legislators
後來經過立法委員
after some surgeons
經過一些外科醫生
Go through a hospital and have a group
經過一科醫院並有團體
say no no no
說啊不行不行
Breast cancer is now the No. 1 cancer in Taiwan
現在台灣乳癌已經是第一號癌症
You should consider individualized medicine for each individual
你應該考慮每一個人的個人化醫療
don't say anything
你不要說什麼
Herto was given only when chemotherapy failed.
化療沒效才給那herto
Only to hersetting
才給hersetting
make it a second medical
把它弄成第二件醫療
it's too late
那來不及了
Should have paid for it from the start
應該一開始就來給付
But our personalized medicine
可是我們個人化醫學的
Another concept is emerging
另外一個概念在產生
Consider the cost
要考慮成本啊
Hersetting costs 800,000 a year
hersetting是一年要80萬
every disease
那每一種病
Everyone said, I want targeted therapy.
大家就說啊我要標靶治療
Why is there so much money to build a country?
那建國家怎麼那麼多錢
So this is our concept of personalized medicine
所以這就是我們個人化醫學的概念
many derived problems
的很多衍生出來的問題
gradually came into being
就逐漸產生了
So in another example
因此在另外一個例子呢
Just another example
就是剛才講的另外一個例子
That's the example we're going to tell you
就是我們要跟大家講的例子
It says that in addition to targeted therapy for cancer
它就說除了癌症的標靶治療之外
Another very successful example
另外還有一個很成功的例子呢
It was published in March of this year
就是發表在今年那個3月份
Just now Vice President Chen mentioned that our Voice Institute
剛才陳副院長提到我們聲音所
With 150 neurologists from 23 hospitals in Taiwan
跟全台灣23家醫院150位神經科醫師
Published in the most beautiful heart in the world
發表在全世界最有美心
This article in one man's medical journal
一個人醫學雜誌的這篇文章
called in the past two years
被稱之為在這一兩年來
One of the two most successful examples of personalized medicine
最成功的個人化醫學的兩個例子當中的一個例子
he does one thing
他做的是一件事情
There are three main ingredients in that thing
那件事情有三個主要的成分
the first is medicine
第一個就是藥
This drug is called Cover Masben
這顆藥就是叫做Cover Masben
what to treat
專門治療什麼
Epilepsy and trigeminal neuralgia
癲兼啊 三叉神經痛啊
Toothache, trigeminal neuralgia
就是牙齒痛就三叉神經痛啊
Sometimes joint pain
有時候關節痛啊
It is also possible to give this Cover Masben
也是能夠給這個Cover Masben
it is a very effective pain reliever
它是一個非常有效的止痛藥
And it can also treat the day
而且還可以治療天間
Also treats bipolar disorder
還可以治療躁鬱症
Many mental illnesses can give it Cover Masben
很多精神疾病都可以給它Cover Masben
because it's cheap
因為很便宜
This is the first we've seen in this study is Cover Masben
這是第一個我們這篇研究看到的就是Cover Masben
What about the second one?
第二個呢
That is to say, this drug has a chance to cause the Steven Johnson just mentioned
就是說這顆藥有機會引起剛才講的Steven Johnson
third factor
第三個因素
who will cause steven johnson
誰會引起Steven Johnson
It's the 1502 genotype.
就是1502基因型啊
Thus a concept arises
因此一個概念就產生
can we check one person first
我們能不能夠先檢查一個人
called HLAV1502 for
叫做HLAV1502進行
For example, in our lecture hall
你譬如說我們這個這個講堂裡面
Someone is 1501, someone is 1503,
有人是1501,有人是1503,
If someone is that 3101, don't be afraid
有人是那個3101,就不怕
But suppose it is 1502
可是假設是1502的話
Had a chance to eat cabbage after this
就有機會吃了卡巴馬斯本之後
It will be that Stephen Johnson who was so serious just now.
就會得剛才這麼嚴重的那個史蒂芬·姜森
Then I'm down here
那我下面這裡呢
Just use our example to tell you
就是利用我們這個例子來跟大家講
Assuming that when personalized medicine is to be
假設要進行個人化醫學的時候
what kind of things should we consider
我們應該考慮什麼樣的事情
We don't just talk
我們並不是很簡單的講說
This 1502, then we will do genetic screening for everyone
這個1502,那我們就給大家做基因篩檢
As far as the whole cabamas this leads to
就整個卡巴馬斯本導致
steven johnson's 1502 words
史蒂芬·姜森是1502的話
In general textbooks it is called
在一般的教科書就稱之為
This is a very interesting example
這是一個非常有趣的例子
be able to put things that should be considered in personalized medicine
能夠把個人化醫學應該考慮的事情
from start to finish
從頭走到尾
So our second half will help
因此我們的後半部就幫
Take everyone through this process once
帶著大家走一次這個過程
What is the first process?
第一個過程是什麼?
In the first process, of course you have to discover
第一個過程你當然要發現
What kind of person eats Kabob Mas powder?
到底什麼樣的人吃了喀布馬斯粉
got that Stephen Johnson so
才會得那個 Stephen Johnson 因此
You mean that in terms of our research
你等於是就我們研究來講
you are looking for related
你要找相關
You have to see if the correlation is strong
你要看這個相關強不強
This correlation-inconsistency
這相關一不一致
So is this correlation causal?
那這個相關到底是因果相關呢
or indirectly related
還是間接相關
And is this factor single factor or multiple factor
而且這個因子是單因子還是多因子
let's look at the first one
我們就來看第一個
How on earth do we find relevant
我們到底如何找到相關
Find related in our medicine
在我們醫學當中找相關
The easiest way is to compare
最簡單的方法就是比較
Comparing who eats more C-B-Z
比較誰比較吃 C-B-Z
the song just now
這剛才的歌要
who will get Stephen Johnson
會得 Stephen Johnson 的人
Better to eat C-B-Z than to get Stephen Johnson
比上吃 C-B-Z 不會得 Stephen Johnson
than two groups
比兩組嘛
let's say gene mutation
來比說基因的變異
1501 1502 1503 3501
1501 1502 1503 3501
look at which gene variant
看哪一種基因變異
Will be super tall with Stephen Johnson
會跟 Stephen Johnson 特別高
tantamount to saying
等於是說
Assuming that the gene mutation
假設這個基因變異的
if it has something to do with the disease
會跟病有關係的話
Because I saw people with stomach allergies taking medicine
因為看到吃藥胃過敏的人
He belongs to 1502
他都是屬於1502
The group of 1502
一五零二這一組
people who are not allergic
是要不會過敏的人
Neither belong to the group of 1502
都不是屬於一五零二這一組
It is indeed our Chen Yuancong
的確是我們這個陳元從
Inspect my colleagues in the firm
驗事我的生意所的同事
In 2004 the world's most famous
在2004年全世界最有名的
This thing discovered by Nature Tikan
Nature Tikan發現的這件事情
Let's start from the top
就大家從上面開始看
he checks 1502 first
他首先檢查一五零二
Discover
發現
People who are allergic to CBZ
吃CBZ會過敏的人
just said
就是剛才講的
this group
這一組
of forty-four
四十四個人當中
hundred percent
百分之百
Generation 1502
代一五零二
compared to taking medicine
相對於吃藥
not allergic
不會過敏的
only three percent
只有百分之三
100% higher than
百分之百比上
You say you are different, do you want to be strong?
你說相不一樣想不想很強
that three percent
那個百分之三
Then look at other positions
那看其他的位置
Ninety-three percent to sixteen percent
百分之九十三比十六
Eighty-one percent to ninety-seven and five to eleven percent
百分之八十一比九十七十五比十一
None of the other locations
其他位置都沒有
first position so strong
第一個位置那麼強
So this is what we just said
所以這就我們剛才講
must think about
一定要想相關
And the cut kind of correlation is
而剪那種相關是
After that, the story is not over
那相關之後還那個故事沒有結束
Are you looking at whether the correlation is causal or indirect?
你要看說這種相關是因果相關還是間接相關
I mean to put it in terms of what I just said
我的意思拿剛才的話來講
Just to show you this picture
就是給大家看到這個圖
I wouldn't say we saw the example
我不會說我們看到這個例子
This is the Vice President Chen
這就是那個陳副院長
When I graduated from Pop with Us
以前在跟我們上流行畢業的時候
often taken example
常常取的例子
You see, people who drink alcohol will get short of breath
你看喝酒的會得氣喘
Why do you get breathless when you drink alcohol?
喝酒怎麼會得氣喘呢
Actually drinkers love to smoke
事實上喝酒的愛抽菸
Smoking actually causes asthma
事實上導致氣喘是抽菸
Then why do you get breathless when you see people who drink alcohol?
那你為什麼看到喝酒的人會得氣喘呢
That's because people who drink have to smoke
那是因為喝酒的人就要抽菸
people who don't drink don't smoke
不喝酒的人不抽菸
What really causes asthma is smoking
真的導致氣喘的是抽菸
So you see the relationship between drinking and asthma
所以你看到喝酒跟氣喘的關係
is an indirect relationship
是一種間接相關
So let's ask a question
因此我們就問一個問題
It is the relationship between 1502 and Stephen Johnson mentioned earlier
就是剛才提到的1502跟這個 Stephen Johnson的關係
Is it the indirect connection between drinking and asthma?
到底是喝酒跟氣喘的這種間接相關呢
Or something between smoking and wheezing?
還是抽菸跟氣喘的這種之間
How do I do it?
那怎麼做呢 我給大家排槓
He said that drinkers also love foot soldiers and wolves
他說喝酒的也愛腳兵狼啊
That foot soldier might actually be causing asthma
那腳兵狼也許真的導致氣喘
Everyone, don't have preconceived notions
大家不要先入為主的觀念喔
Maybe the cause of the asthma is the foot soldier wolf
說不定氣喘的原因是腳兵狼啊
That's why drinkers love cigarettes and drinkers love foot soldiers
因此喝酒的人愛抽菸 喝酒的人愛腳兵狼
then you can't figure it out
那你搞不清楚說
So in the end the cause of the asthma is smoking, drinking or foot soldiers
那到底那個氣喘的原因是抽菸 喝酒還是腳兵狼
Then how to clarify? The medical scientist said
那怎麼樣釐清 那醫學家就說
That’s no way, you need to use other indicators
那沒辦法 那你要多用其他的指標
For example, do you see if a finger turns yellow?
譬如說 你看一個手指頭有沒有變黃
Because of smoking for a long time, the fingers will turn yellow
因為抽菸久了 手指頭會變黃
Can you see if a person coughs? If you cough for a long time, you will cough
你看一個人會不會咳嗽 咳嗽久了就會咳嗽
Can you see if a person will have oral diseases?
你看一個人會不會口腔病變
Because of oral lesions of the foot soldier wolf
因為腳兵狼口腔病變
hypothetical hypothetical you can't tell
假設 假設真的你沒有辦法分辨
Smoking or foot soldier wolf is asthma
抽菸還是腳兵狼是氣喘
Then suppose it's the foot soldier wolf that really caused the asthma
那假設真的導致氣喘的是腳兵狼的話
what will you see what will you see
你會看到什麼 你會看到
Oral lesions, yellow fingers, cough
有口腔病變 有黃手指 有咳嗽
No oral lesions, yellow fingers, cough
比上 沒有口腔病變 有黃手指 有咳嗽的
This man is breathing high
這個人氣喘來的高
So it's a very simple principle of medicine
所以這是醫學一個很簡單的原理
You have to further distinguish
你要進一步分辨說
who is directly related
誰是直接相關
still healthy
還是健康的健康關
You are looking for more indicators
你要找更多的指標
come to meet, to clarify
來交集,來釐清說
Who is Brother Yuan?
到底誰是元兄
Therefore, that
因此,那個
After academician Chen and the others discovered this correlation
那個陳院士他們發現這種相關之後
To see such a strong correlation
要看看說這種那麼強的相關
who is strong
誰很強
But is it directly related?
可是到底是不是直接相關呢
So he was there
因此他就在那個
That is, we look at this
就是說,我們看這個
It is the 1.502 mentioned just now
就是在剛才講的1.502
right here, elsewhere in the gene
就是在這裡,在基因的其他位置
because he will be together
因為會被他一起
Take off the water, maybe it's the gene next to him
脫下水的,也許是他旁邊的基因
I'm just showing you this picture
就是我用這個圖給大家看
that is
就是說
You can see that the position of a gene is related to the disease
你看一個基因的位置跟病有關
He may be reflecting his right gene
他也許反映的是他右邊的基因
also left gene
也是左邊的基因
like the example i always give
就如同我常常舉的例子
I take the high-speed rail
我搭高鐵
to Taichung, fly out of Taichung
到台中,飛出台中
found my friend coming in to pick me up
發現我的朋友進來接我
I said happily in my heart, why do you think I'm coming
我心裡面高興說,你怎麼想到我要來
you were so enthusiastic before
你之前那麼熱情
you run to the train station to pick me up
你跑到火車站來接我
My friend said you change the car
我朋友說你換駕
I'm not coming to pick you up at all
我根本不來接你
He came to pick up his girlfriend
他來接他女朋友
why
為什麼呢
because me and his girlfriend
因為我跟他的女朋友
Take the same high-speed train
搭同樣一部高鐵列車來
what does he mean
他意思是什麼
Mom and Dad gave us
爸爸媽媽給我們的
Not sent to us one by one
不是一個一個機器發給我們的
what mom and dad gave us is
爸爸媽媽給我們的是
Chromosomes sent to us one by one
一條一條染色體發給我們的
So you find that one of the chromosomes
所以你發現某一條染色體當中
A certain position is related to the disease
某一個位置跟病有關
Maybe it's the chromosome
反應的也許是這條染色體
next to him
他旁邊的位置
People who take the high-speed train with me
跟我一起搭高鐵列車的人
maybe that's the one
也許才是那個
who my friend wants to pick up
我朋友想接的人
so what to do
因此怎麼辦
Divorce is just like saying
離親就是如同剛剛講
Then you do a few more
那你多做幾個
Therefore, the laboratory of Academician Chen Yuanhong
因此那個陳元宏院士的實驗室
What are you doing near 1502 just now?
就在剛才這個1502的附近做什麼
HRAR is other
HRAR就是其他
I will read it to everyone
我就念給大家
That's the first one above
就是上面第一個就是說
private medicine for allergies
私藥為過敏的
70 vs. 46
70對46
looks like no difference
看起來沒什麼差別
93 against 13
93對13
90 to 4
90變4
start raising
開始墊高囉
Change 6, 98 change 4 are very high
變6,98變4都很高
95 becomes 13, and the relative lower one starts
95變13,開始相關的低一點
68 becomes 16, lower
68變16,更低
equal to these you can see
等於是這些你可以看到
Starts low, then the correlation gets stronger and stronger
開始很低,然後相關越來越強
To the lowest, the area where the results intersect
到最低,結果交集出的那個區域裡面
The only gene is just said HRAB
唯一的基因就是剛才講HRAB
So here is to find the relevant
所以這裡就是找到剛才那種相關
may be directly related than we think
可能是直接相關,而不是我們想的
indirectly related
間接相關
On the other hand, this correlation is in our medicine
另外一方面,這個相關在我們醫學當中
That means there must be so-called consistency
那說那一定要有所謂的一致性
What about consistency?
什麼那一致性呢?
different people, different times, different places
就不同的人,不同的時間,不同的地點
The results of the research done should be the same
做的研究結果要一樣
Then the research of 1502 from the 2004 of Chen Academician Tang
那就1502的研究從陳院士堂的2004年
After publishing Nature
發表Nature之後
Many countries in the world, including Japan, South Korea, Germany, France
世界上很多國家,包括日本、韓國、德國、法國
learn from them to do experiments
就學他們做實驗
It turned out that a very interesting thing
結果就發現一件很有趣的事情
Everyone look to the right first
大家先看右邊
There are four regions
有四個地區
Including Taiwan, Hong Kong, Thailand and Washington
包括了台灣、香港、泰國以及華盛頓
South China, the south of China
華南地區 中國的南方喔
Discover
發現
CBZ with
CBZ跟
Steven Johnson's relationship is strong
Steven Johnson的關係很強
on the contrary
反之
What kind of Japan is our neighbor's Japan?
像什麼日本 我們鄰居的日本喔
South Korea
韓國
that german french
那個德國 法國
Could not find the relationship between CBZ and Steven Johnson
找不到CBZ跟Steven Johnson的關係
Why
為什麼
here Miri is here
這裡 米里在這裡
Because none of these people carry 1502 at all
因為這些人 根本沒有人帶1502
It is equal to that they are all 1501
等於是他們都是1501
1503 3101
1503 3101
Others wake up
其他的驚醒啊
on the contrary
反之
Those strongly correlated regions
那些強相關的地區喔
Just like us in Taiwan, like us in this classroom
就像我們台灣 像我們在這個教室裡面
5 out of 100 people
100個人就有5個
200 people have 10 people with 1502 ah
200個人就有10個人是帶1502啊
therefore
因此
1502 high area
1502高的地區
have a strong correlation
有強的相關
1502 low area
1502低的地區
no strong correlation
沒有強的相關
This is another form of consistency
這也是另外一種形式的一致性
tell us
告訴我們說
this
這個
Probably the culprit of the disease
大概是疾病的元凶
So it's called
所以這是所謂
You really want to personalize medicine
你真的要做個人化醫學
Of course do some research
當然要做一些研究
Need some evidence
要有一些實證的資料來看說
How strong is the correlation
到底相關有多強
Whether the correlation is direct or indirect
相關是直接相關還是間接相關
And we don't have time to mention it to you
而且我們時間有些沒辦法跟大家提到
Is it single factor or multifactor
到底是單因子還是多因子
The first point is really just the first step
第一點實在是第一步而已
second step
第二步
We just compared the past and the past are more relevant
我們剛才比以來比去都是比相關
But there is no actual data
可是沒有一個實際的資料
Let's get to the bottom of this
來了解說到底這個
How must be the factor
定是怎麼產生的因子
Second, you still have laboratory evidence
第二點你還有實驗室的證據
Then Chen Yuan has done a very good job since TV
那陳元從電視他們就做得非常好
They will come to explain first
他們就先來了解說
why Steve
為什麼 Steve
Steven Johnson skin turns up
Steven Johnson 皮膚會翻起來
To paraphrase the sentence just now
用套用剛才那句話來講
Steven Johnson is our skin cells
Steven Johnson 就是我們的皮膚細胞
to commit suicide
去自殺了
like once after suicide
就像一旦自殺之後
Just bubble water, soak water a few more
就起水泡水泡水幾台多
turn the whole skin over
就把皮膚整個翻過來
Therefore, Chen Yuan first researched from the TV side
因此陳元從電視那邊就先來研究說
Exactly a Steven Johnson guy
到底一個 Steven Johnson 的人
the place where the blisters
起水泡的那個地方
In the end the difference
到底差別
Where is the genetic difference
基因差別在哪裡
this looks complicated
這看起來很複雜
actually a bit of skin color
事實上一點的膚色
Three types of organizations, the first one you will see
三種組織 給大家看到的 第一個
The blistered tissue of Steven Johnson's patient
Steven Johnson的病人的起水泡的那個組織
He took out the tissue with blisters and the second one
他把水泡那個組織拿出來 第二個呢
man of steven johnson
Steven Johnson的人
The Tissue Without Blisters by Steven Johnson
Steven Johnson的 沒有起水泡的那個組織
Just to get blood cells as a control
就是拿到血球來當作對照嘛
The same person is sick and not sick, and compared to a third person
同樣一個人有病跟沒病 以及比上第三個人
It is the blood cells of ordinary people, you, me, and other healthy people
就是一般人你我他大家健康的人的血球
Let's compare some genes related to cell suicide
來比 比一些跟細胞自殺有關係的基因
It turned out that one of the genes was called Greolizing
結果他就發現 其中一個基因就是叫做Greolizing
You can see that the tissue in the blister is performing better than healthy cells
你看起水泡那個組織的表現量 比上健康的細胞
Or the patient's healthy cells are significantly higher
或者是病人健康的細胞 很明顯的高很多
You said this is also related to cytology?
你說這個也是細胞學的相關啊
Is this correlation causal?
那這種相關是不是因果相關
He mentioned this kind of Greolizing here, after all, it is to extract the organization to do it.
他把這種Greolizing說這裡畢竟是把組織抽出來做
If you really want to see the sick place, you can really get the performance of Greolizing
那真的來看得病的那個地方 就真的去染Greolizing的表現
indeed performance
的確是表現
Show this coffee color
有表現這咖啡色
no performance is no color
沒有表現就是沒顏色
The upper left corner is the place where the blister
左上角就是那個起水泡的地方
The lower right corner is where there is no blister
右下角就是沒有起水泡的地方
where he gets sick
他看得病的地方
also found that
也的確發現說
blisters
起水泡的地方
It's not as good as being sexually expressive
的確不如要性表現很高
But these are just related
可是這些都只是相關而已啊
what kind of related
什麼樣相關
have blisters have personal sex
有起水泡有個人愛性
no blisters no personal sex
沒起水泡沒有個人愛性
But this personal love
可是這種個人愛性
is it right?
到底是不是
What about Steven Johnson's causality?
Steven Johnson的因果關係呢
he is doing an experiment
他在做了一個實驗
just put the cells
就把細胞
One blue dyes one cell
一個藍色就染一個細胞
what to make him
給他泡什麼
bubble personalities
泡個人愛性
You see, after having some personal sex
你看一泡了個人愛性之後
will turn red
就會變成紅色
red is a dye
紅色是染一個染料
That's called Ernestine Fier
那個就是叫做 Ernestine Fier
What is Ernestine Fierce?
Ernestine Fierce是什麼指標
indicator of suicide
自殺的指標
turn out to be
原來
In terms of cytology
就細胞學來看
Cell de-soaking after personal love sex
細胞去泡了個人愛性之後
cells will have
細胞就會有
Aptosis kills itself
Aptosis就會自殺
Therefore, at the cytological level
因此在細胞學的層面
proved
印證了
Personal love is the cause of cell
個人愛性是導致細胞
Causes of Aptosis
Aptosis的原因
then you are just cells
那你就只是細胞而言
So he beat Glasgow to the rat organization
因此他把哥拉斯因一打到老鼠的組織
After two hours, four hours, five hours
開始打兩小時、四小時、五小時之後
The epidermal cells of mice produce a lot of aptoces
老鼠的表皮細胞就產生很多aptoces的狀況
Therefore, it has been confirmed in front of zoology
因此在動物學前面就印證了
The blistered one that Gerasin and the patient saw
哥拉斯因跟病人所看到的那個起水泡的
causal correlation
呈現的因果相關
So he first discovered in 2008
因此他首先在2008年就發現了
Why One Can Get Stephen Johnson's Molecular Gene Transfer
一個人為什麼會得斯蒂芬·姜森的分子基轉
The base transfer is in the vesicular tissue cells
那個基轉就是水泡組織細胞當中
There are many Grassin performances
有很多哥拉斯因的表現
The expression of these corusoids will make the cell aptoces
這些哥拉斯因的表現會讓細胞aptoces
But this has no answer
可是這個還沒有答案
Because the answer we need is
因為我們需要的答案是
Then why eating CBZ will produce Gorax
那為什麼吃CBZ會有哥拉斯因產生
more importantly
更重要的是
Why only the 51502 person will behave
為什麼只有那個51502的人才會表現
The following is the result of more than a year of hard work
下面這一點就是這一年多來的努力成果
this hasn't been published yet
這還沒有發表
Let's keep it a secret
大家一起來保守秘密
he first
他就首先
He found someone who was allergic to CVZ
他就找了吃CVZ會過敏的人
Sorry, patients who eat CVZ
對不起 吃CVZ的病人
take out his blood cells
把他血球細胞拿出來
Treat him to the CVZ and get his blood cells out
給他處理CVZ跟把他血球拿出來
Treat the general physiological experiment water
處理一般的那個生理實驗水
It was found that these patients
結果發現這些病人
His cells once processed CVZ
他的細胞一旦處理CVZ之後
As mentioned earlier, the performance of Glienoxyne is particularly high.
剛才講Glienoxyne表現就特別特別的高
Therefore, the initial establishment of CVZ
因此就初步建立起CVZ
Let the cells show the causal relationship between Glienoxyne and each other
會讓細胞表現Glienoxyne彼此之間的因果關係
Assuming everyone will believe that
假設大家會相信說
I just talked about Glienoxyne because it causes cellular Atosis
我剛才講了Glienoxyne因為導致細胞Atosis
That's half the answer
那這樣子答案解決了一半
But another bigger doubt is
可是另外更大的疑惑就是
Then why only 1502 waited to take medicine to be like this
那為什麼只有1502等吃藥才會這樣子
It's not 1502 it doesn't look like this
它不是1502就不會這樣子
it's better to do a study
它就做更好的一個研究
it is written in the heart
它就心裡面寫出來
immune response in the body
身體裡面的免疫反應
basically relying on what we just said
基本上是靠著我們剛才講的什麼
HLA
HLA
We say that everyone has
我們講大家身體裡面都有
HA has HA1, HA2, 150
HA有HA1、HA2、150
What is the main function of this HA
這HA主要的功能是什麼
HA is a very important molecule that compares the difference between you and me
HA是比較你我差別的一個很主要的一個分子
we often talk
我們常常講說
This person will have that allergic reaction
這個人會有那個過敏反應
In other words, all organ transplants are rejected
或者是說這個器官移植都有排斥
Why is there rejection
為什麼會有排斥
you are 1502
你是1502
I am 1501
我是1501
You kindly donate your blood to me
你好心把你的血捐給我
1502 meets 1502
1502碰到1502
1501 Two HAs are different
1501兩個HA不一樣
cause allergic reaction
就會引起過敏反應
Why
為什麼
Because HA is recognized by some immune cells
因為HA會被一些免疫細胞所辨識
immune cell discovery says
免疫細胞發現說
this is not mine
這個不是我的
release some hormones
就放出一些激素
Let cells produce aposis
讓細胞產生aposis
So it thinks of one thing in its heart
因此它在心裡面就想一件事
will that
那會不會
will this medicine
會不會這顆藥
Will be stuck in HLA
會卡在HLA
Let one of my immune cells follow my skin cells
讓一個我的免疫細胞跟我的皮膚細胞
It was a family
本來是一家人啊
My immune cells should say
我的免疫細胞應該會說啊
This is my own
這個是自己人啊
Will this, this, this medicine get stuck on it?
會不會這個這個這顆藥會卡在上面之後
let my immune cells say
讓我的免疫細胞說啊
If you don't understand this thing
這個東西看不懂看不懂的話
toxins
就會對它產生毒素
So this my skin cells will produce atosis
因此這個我的皮膚細胞就要產生atosis
He came to apply for this matter
他就來應徵這件事情
But after applying for this matter
可是應徵這件事情之後
He did a very important research
他做了一個很重要的一個研究
That is to say, everyone assumes that slightly
就是說大家假設是稍微
Those who have studied immunology in high school all say one sentence
讀過高中的免疫學都講一句話
That sentence means
那句話就是說
The HA of this cell shows that it has been processed by the cell
這個細胞的HA表現的是經過細胞處理的
It's like saying we have the flu today
等於是說我們今天有流感
After the flu virus enters our body
流感病毒跑到我們身體裡面之後
will be processed by cells in the body
會藉由身體裡面細胞的處理之後
After processing the flu protein
處理之後才會把流感的蛋白質
Expressed on HA
表現在HA上面
Immune cells can't understand
讓免疫細胞看不懂
So he thought the pill was so small
因此他就想這顆藥那麼小
Those medicines are very small
那藥都很小啊
Does it need to be processed by that cell to manifest?
是不是還要藉由那個細胞的處理才會表現呢
So he did two very important studies
因此他就做了兩個很重要的研究
Also this study is also the one that hasn't been published
同樣這個研究也是那個還沒有發表
The first study is to put
第一個研究呢就是把
It's a different cell
這不同的細胞喔
Putting the difference to it handles CBZ
把不同給它處理CBZ
handle two situations
處理兩種狀況
The first condition is blood cells
第一種狀況就是血球
The second is the blood cells or cells
第二種就是這個血球或者是細胞
The second condition is to shake the cell
第二種狀況就是把這個細胞搖一搖
He's here to test the drug after all.
他就是來檢驗說到底這顆藥
The relationship with this HA
跟這個HA的關係
Are they really strong together?
到底是很強的接在一起呢
Just shake it and it's gone
還是搖一搖就沒有了
As a result you can see that
結果你看你可以發現
Gave CBZ or a drug that looks like CBZ
給了CBZ或者是構造很像CBZ的藥
Assuming that before shaking
假設是沒搖之前
immune response so strong
免疫反應那麼強
After shaking you shake this cell
搖了之後你把這個細胞搖搖搖
he has no immune response
他就沒有免疫反應
represent one thing
代表一件事情
That thing is important for immunology
那件事情對免疫學很重要
that thing is to say
那件事情就是說
Don't take this medicine the way of traditional flu
這一顆藥不要走傳統的流感的路
Traditional Flu Way
傳統流感路
After the flu virus is eaten by this cell, it is cut into several pieces
那流感病毒被這個細胞吃下去之後切好幾塊
Then the strong ones will stick to the HLA
然後很強的就會黏在HLA上面
But from this experiment, it seems that after shaking it, it disappears.
可是從這個實驗看起來搖一搖就不見了
The representative said that the relationship between this drug and HLA is very slight.
代表說這顆藥跟HLA的關係是很輕的一個這樣
glued together
黏接在一起
Does not seem to require treatment by cells
好像不需要藉由細胞的處理
This is the first one
這是第一個
to prove this
為了要印證這件事情
He's going to treat the cells with another drug
他要把這細胞處理另外一個藥
Called Paraformer Op.1
叫做Paraformer Op.1
What is the main function of the main chemical drug in this medicine
這顆藥的主要化學藥的主要功能是什麼
Let the outside of the cell build a layer of copper and iron walls
讓細胞的外面建一層銅牆鐵壁
where is the purpose
目的在哪裡
keep outside things out
讓外面的東西進不去
what's inside can't get in
裡面的東西進不來
he means
他的意思是說
Assuming that this drug does not need to be processed by cells
假設這一顆藥不需要藉由細胞的處理
there will be a reaction
就會有反應的話
That means you build an iron wall
那代表你建一個銅牆鐵壁
had no effect on the stimulation of the immune response
對免疫反應的刺激一點影響都沒有
everyone can see
大家可以看到
Immune response before and after dosing
給藥之前給藥之後免疫反應
no difference
沒有絲毫的差別
represents what
代表什麼
Means this medicine is not needed
代表這顆藥不需要
Run into the cell and be processed by the cell
跑到細胞裡面藉由細胞的處理
send it out
再送出來
Because you borrowed the same foot blood wall
因為你藉了同腳血壁
The contents should not be delivered
應該裡面的東西送不出來
Things outside can't get in.
外面的東西進不去啊
therefore
因此
It leads to a very important basis transfer
它就引申出一個很重要的基轉
that is
就是說
CBG is such a small medicine
CBG這顆那麼小的藥
immune response
所引起的免疫反應
Probably not the traditional flu route
大概不是走傳統的那個流感的那條路
It will be directly stuck on this HA
是直接會卡在這個HA上面
With this evidence
有了這個證據之後
It can directly do an experiment
它直接就可以做一個實驗
that experiment is
那個實驗就是
Check the annual ability of CBG and HA
檢驗CBG跟HA的年間能力啊
therefore
因此
The famous result comes out
這個有名的結果就出來了
someone is 1501
有人是1501
someone is 1502
有人是1502
Someone 1503
有人1503
Someone 4001
有人4001
Someone 5101
有人5101
View separately
分別來看
CBG is the drug just now
CBG就剛才那個藥
or strong structure
或者是構造很強的
Much like ECBG
很像的ECBG
see separately
分別看
The annual capacity of CBG and 1501
CBG跟1501的年間能力
It is tantamount to directly examining the two-year
它等於是直接去檢驗兩個年間
Because since we don't directly deal with
因為既然不要直接處理
you can see
你就可以看說
will it stick to it
它會不會跟它黏在一起
it turns out
結果就發現
1501 can't stick 1501
1501黏不住1501
Live in 103 years, live in 4001 years, live in 510 years, live in 510 years
103年不住,4001年不住,510年不住,510年不住
only what?
只有什麼?
1502 is closely related to the strong adhesion of this medicine
1502跟這顆藥的黏著力強的藥密
So, the mystery gradually picks up
所以,謎底逐漸接下
Why only 1502 etc. are allergic?
為什麼只有1502等會過敏?
that is because
那是因為
Everyone takes CVD medicine
大家都吃CVD這顆藥
But only after 1502 took the medicine
可是只有1502等吃了藥之後
This pill will stick to it very strongly
這顆藥會強強很強烈的黏在上面
1501 will be sticky, but shake it and it will disappear
1501會黏,可是搖一搖就不見了
1503 Shake and disappear
1503搖一搖就不見了
But only 1502 will stick to it strongly
可是只有1502等會強強的黏在上面
Can't shake it down
搖不下來
Then you stick to one cell, of course you don’t understand
那你黏一細胞,當然看不懂啊
Because there is an extra piece of this kind of thing on the top
因為是上面多了一塊這種東西
Release the Genericin just mentioned to him
對他放出剛才講的Genericin
Once the Genericin is released
一旦Genericin放出去之後
The Apocytus just seen produced
剛才看到的Apocytus就產生了
So these bits and pieces understand the evidence
所以這些零零懂懂證據
Including the discovery that Genericin is a part of Apocytus
包括剛才發現Genericin是Apocytus的一
and Keeneb explains 1502
以及記尼布解釋1502
Why do only 1502 and so on get sick?
為什麼只有1502等才得病?
So found out that
因此就找到了說
basic evidence
基礎的證據
So for a personalized medicine
所以對一個個人化醫學而言
Why is it called the most successful story abroad
為什麼這國外稱之為最成功的一個故事
You will start with the initial
你會從最初的相關
This is then further correlated with laboratory evidence
然後這相關之後進一步用實驗室的證據
to find the basal rotation that it says takes place
來找到它所謂發生的基轉
With these foundational transfers,
有了這些基礎基轉之後
We can really use it in clinical use
我們真的就可以用在臨床的使用
But clinical application is not as easy as imagined
可是臨床使用並不是想像當中那麼容易
This is why our study
這就是為什麼我們這篇研究
Reasons to be in the New England Journal of Medicine
能夠上新英格蘭醫學雜誌的原因
The reason for this being in the New England Journal of Medicine
這個上新格蘭醫學雜誌的原因
definitely not that we found
絕對不是說我們發現
CBZ will cause Didi to do this because of 1502
CBZ會因為1502會導致滴滴這樣
what are the details
這是什麼細節
Discovered in 2004
2004年就發現了
And the academician and his laboratory also found that the base transfer
而且那個成院士他們實驗室也發現這個基轉了
One of the greatest successes of this study is that
這個研究最大的一個成功點就是
we really proved that
我們真的證明了說
Genetic Screening Before Medication
用藥之前的基因篩檢
under the right circumstances
在適當的環境之下
in an appropriate clinical setting
在適當的臨床環境之下
Genetic screening before this medication
這個用藥之前的基因篩檢
Allergic reactions after anti-depressant medication
就能夠抑鬱防用藥之後的過敏反應
then let's see
那我們就來看看
What does the research here tell you?
這邊研究跟大家講的是哪些點
This thing is known to everyone
這個東西對大家了解
Personalized medicine is really used clinically
個人化醫學真的用在臨床上
is a very important thing
是很重要的一件事情
That is what we often say
也就是我們常常講的
You have to take into account positive predictive value and negative predictive value
你要考慮到陽性預測值跟陰性預測值
What kind of positive predictive value negative predictive value
什麼樣的陽性預測值 陰性預測值
We see that the horizontal axis is
我們看到橫軸就是
Allergic to medicine
吃藥會過敏的
There are two kinds of people who are not allergic to medicine
吃藥不會過敏的 有兩種
The heavy axis is the check
重軸就是檢查
1502 is positive
1502是陽性的
1502 is negative
1502是陰性的
1502 people will be allergic to medicine
1502的人吃藥會過敏
Than 1502 will not be allergic to medicine
比1502吃藥不會過敏
Strong correlation
相關很強
we just said
我們剛才講
The correlation is about 1357 times
相關是大概是1357倍
But a strong correlation does not necessarily mean
可是相關很強不一定代表
You can use it in personalized medicine
你就可以用在個人化醫學
because of personalized medicine considerations
因為個人化醫學考慮
Not so-called sensitivity and specificity
不是所謂的敏感度跟特異度
What sensitivity specificity is
什麼敏感度特異度就是
among people allergic to medicine
吃藥過敏的人當中
How many people are in 1502
有多少人是在1502
Among those who are not allergic to medicine
吃藥不會過敏的人當中
How many people are not in 1502
有多少人不是在1502
Sensitivity is especially high
敏感度都特意度很高
This stuff doesn't mean anything to patients.
這個東西對病人一點意思都沒有
What does the patient care about?
病人關心的是什麼?
count from above
從上面算下來
suppose i'm positive
假設我是陽性
Will I be allergic to the medicine?
我吃藥會不會過敏?
assume i'm negative
假設我是陰性
Is it okay if I take the medicine?
我吃藥是不是就沒事?
This is the so-called positive awareness value
這個就是所講的陽性意識值
Negative Awareness
陰性意識值
Positive Awareness Points, Negative Awareness Points
陽性意識值、陰性意識值
basically depends on sensitivity and specificity
基本上是決定於敏感度跟特意度
and to what extent
以及相關的程度
In terms of whether 1502 is allergic to medicine
就這個1502跟吃藥會不會過敏而言
Positive consciousness value is ultra-low, only 5.6%
陽性意識值超低只有5.6%
Only 5.6%
只要5.6%
Suppose you are 1502 positive
假設你是1502陽性
As far as we are concerned, there are about 10 of the 200 people
就我們講這200個人大概有10個
you eat CBG
你吃CBG
He said my dentist gave me CBG
他說我的牙科醫師給我開CBG
Do not worry
放心啦
There will really be 4 out of 100 talents and 5
真的會有4的100個人才5個
95% of people are fine
95%的人都沒事
Then you say of course checking this is useless
那你說當然檢查這個沒用啊
But this research
可是這個研究
The most important thing about this TES is the negative awareness value
這個TES最重要是陰性意識值
close to 100%
接近100%
99.9%
99.9%
what negative district medical set value
什麼陰性區醫設值
if you are negative
假設你是陰性的話
that is
就是
Almost you don't have to worry that you will be allergic to the medicine
幾乎你不要擔心你吃藥會過敏
is B
就是B
B plus the lower of the first cent
B加第一分之低
Just assuming you're a negative person
就是假設你是陰性的人的話
you probably
你大概
Take medicine 99.9%
吃藥99.9%
not allergic
不會過敏
So this is for a patient
所以這個才是對一個病人而言
one thing I care about most
最關心的一件事
I am positive can I eat or not
我陽性我能吃不能吃
I am negative can eat can not eat
我陰性能吃不能吃
Just CBZ and Steven Johnson
就CBZ跟Steven Johnson
With 1502 and CBZ cited by Steven Johnson
跟1502跟CBZ引所引起Steven Johnson
Although the positive predictive value is not very good
陽性預測值雖然不太好
negative predictive value
可是陰性預測值
almost super high
幾乎超高
Once you tell people that if you are Naked
一告訴人家說假設你是Naked的話
you can almost safely take your medicine
你幾乎就可以放心吃藥
that's what we just said
就是我們剛剛講的
we are in our holy clinic
我們就在我們聖醫所
in two years
就在兩年當中
invited in Taiwan
邀請了在台灣
The help of 150 neurologists in 23 hospitals within two years
23家醫院150位神經科醫師的幫忙在兩年之內
A total of invited
一共邀請了
4,855 patients who had the opportunity to take CBZ
有機會吃CBZ的4,855位病人
Genetic screening before medication
先做用藥之前的基因篩檢
Decide if the assumption is negative
決定假設是陰性的話
Said please rest assured to take medicine
說請你放心吃藥
positive?
陽性的呢
that means please be careful
就是說請你要小心
you better change your medicine
你最好換藥
How many are negative?
陰性的有多少呢
92.3%
92.3%
positive?
陽性的呢
7.7%
7.7%
The 7.7% said
這7.7%的人就說
please change your medicine
請你換藥
because
因為
Although you are only 5.6%
雖然你只有5.6%
But
可是
Professor Stephen is so serious
史蒂芬教授那麼嚴重啊
you better not eat
你最好不要吃
but what is important
可是重要的是什麼
If it is negative
假設是陰性的話
you can rest assured to eat
你放心去吃
So feel free to eat if you are negative
所以陰性的放心去吃
positive dressing change
陽性的換藥
Then start tracking for two months
那就開始追蹤兩個月
Let's talk
來看說
Is it by this
是不是藉由這種
Genetic Screening Before Medication
用藥之前的基因篩檢
Can really prevent after medication
真的能夠預防用藥之後的
allergic skin reaction
皮膚過敏反應
At the beginning, of course we counted
那一開始我們當然統計
masculine and feminine
陽性跟陰性的人
Neurologists in Taiwan
到底台灣地區的神經醫科醫師
Who will drive CBZ?
到底誰會開CBZ呢
Results Among our more than 4,800 patients
結果在我們4800多位病人當中
14% are bumps
14%是顛簸
Then there is 54.14% neuralgia
然後有去的是54.14%的神經痛
The vast majority of patients in Taiwan who take CBZ
台灣絕大部分吃CBZ的病人
One out of two suffers from neuralgia
兩個就有一個人是神經痛
Only 14.24% of codes and
只有14.24%的典兼
What about other neurological symptoms?
那其他還有什麼神經症狀
So it's just that we start with the basic data of the patient
所以就只有我們開始病人的基本資料
what we just said
那我們剛剛講
800 people in this world do genetic screening first
這個世間八百位先做基因篩檢
Follow up for two months
然後進行兩個月的追蹤
Negative take medicine lightly
陰性放輕吃藥
If positive, ask him to change the medicine
陽性就請他換藥
As a result, during these two months
結果在這個兩個月當中
Although we cannot avoid
我們雖然不能夠避免掉
It's positive and negative
這是陽性跟陰性
Those symptoms such as itching
那些一些症狀譬如說會癢
rash, blisters
會有紅疹、會起水泡
There are different situations of mouth ulcers and itching
口腔會潰癢有不同的情形
among the positive
在陽性的人當中
among negative people
陰性的人當中
more or less there will still be some
多多少少都還是會有一些
a slightly uncomfortable allergic reaction
比較稍微一點不太舒服的過敏反應
itchy blisters
癢起水泡
But what?
可是呢
What we care about is the following
我們關心的是下面這個
but in this world
可是在這個世間
Of the 4800 patients
4800位病人當中
Positive patients are 0
陽性病人是0
Negative patients are 0
陰性病人是0
from now on
從此之後
no more steven johnson
再也沒有Steven Johnson
Among the 4800 patients
這4800位病人當中
Although we can't
雖然我們沒有辦法
completely prevent
完全的預防掉
The comparisons just mentioned
剛才講的那些比較
mild allergic reaction
輕微一點的過敏反應
But the worst Steven Johnson
可是最嚴重的Steven Johnson
Among our 4800 patients
在我們4800位病人
During the two-month follow-up
兩個月的追蹤當中
completely invisible
完全的看不到了
so this is
所以這就是
What the New Infectious Medicine Journal said is that
那個新感染醫學照雜誌講的就是說
by pre-medication
藉由用藥之前
1502 Genetic Screening
1502的基因篩檢
can really avoid
真的能夠避免掉
Really take that CBZ
真的把那個CBZ
caused by steven johnson
所引起的Steven Johnson
just avoid it completely
就完全的避免掉
He said why he succeeded
他說為什麼會成功
There are several conditions for success
成功有幾個條件
Although these conditions are examples of our study
這些條件雖然是我們這個研究的例子
But everyone is going further
可是大家也是進一步的
We have to think about it at the end and say
我們在最後要思考一下說
If you want to succeed as a personalized medicine
你一個個人化醫學要成功的話
There are several conditions
有幾個條件
First
第一個
The Light of Our Taiwan
我們台灣之光
You have to check CBZ very well
你要很好的檢查CBZ
then you should get checked
那你要該去做檢查
Taiwan's medical and public health standards are very high
台灣的醫療水準 公共衛生水準很高
It is equivalent to the clinical level of a country's public health
等於是一個國家的公共衛生臨床的水準
I have to be very tall to be qualified to say that I want to do personalized medicine
要很高才有資格說我要做個人化醫學
Otherwise, you can't even diagnose the disease.
不然的話你連病都沒有辦法診斷
I can't figure out whether it is the drug diagnosis, the red diagnosis or the lung itching
都搞不清楚說到底是藥物診還是紅診還是那個肺癢
How can you do personalized medicine if you can’t figure it out?
你都搞不清楚的話你怎麼有辦法做個人化醫學
so it was a great success
所以這是一個很成功
A very important condition of this study in Taiwan is that
台灣這篇研究一個很重要的一個條件就是
Taiwan's own medical and public health standards are high
台灣本身醫療公共衛生的水準高
The following more detailed reasons, for example, the first reason
下面更細節的原因譬如說第一個原因
We're close to 100% negative predictive value
我們接近100%的陰性預測值
So this is a very successful drug in this study
所以這是這個研究一個很成功的藥素
100% negative predictive value
100%的陰性預測值
Just assuming that's the case, take the medicine with confidence.
就是假設是那個的話就放心吃藥
At this point, everyone is thinking about the relationship between breast cancer and vegetarianism just now.
這一點大家在想到剛才什麼乳癌跟吃素的關係
Sugar content is not related to obesity
糖量不跟肥胖的關係
Think of these positive healers, negative healers
想這些陽性醫療者 陰性醫療者
you will understand
你就了解說
why why those chronic diseases
為什麼 為什麼那些慢性病
There is no way yet to take into account a person's genetic status
還沒有辦法考慮一個人的基因狀況
risk of disease to a person
對一個人的得病的危險性
make a very accurate assessment
做很精準的評估
Caused by 1502 and CBG
因為1502跟CBG所引起的
Steven Johnson Negative Healers Are Only Nearly 100%
Steven Johnson 陰性醫療者只接近百分之百
So we can safely say
所以我們可以很放心地說
You're Nectin you're hardly weak at any price
你是Nectin 你幾乎不要弱任何代價
Just go take your medicine, it's fine
你就去吃藥 就沒關係
This is the first requirement for success
這是第一個 成功的要件
Second, did he think of one thing?
第二個 他就有沒有想到一件事情
When we were doing this research it was
我們在做這個研究的時候是
alone alone
一個人 一個人
Deciding only after diagnosis
診斷之後才開始決定
To take medicine or not to take medicine
可以吃藥 還是不能吃藥
You just want to die alone
你就想 一個人痛得要死了
You said you have to wait, wait a day, wait two days
你說 你要等 等一天 等兩天
tell you it's positive positive
告訴你是陽性 陽性
So the more successful elements of this study
所以這個研究更成功的要件
This sounds uneducated
這個聽起來沒有什麼學問
But you're talking about clinically important
可是你在講 臨床上很重要
Because our testing reagents
因為我們的檢驗試劑
results in three hours
三個小時就有結果
Send the report and delay
發報告 再拖延
Another two days
再拖也有兩天
So this also sounds uneducated
所以這也是聽起來沒有學問
But this is also the basic spirit of personalized medicine.
可是這也是個人化醫學的基本精神啊
Suppose you want to wait a year and a half by yourself
假設你要一個人等個一年半載
just said you can take medicine
才說你可以吃藥
People have already died of pain
人家老早就痛死了
People quit a long time ago
人家老早就不幹了
So here's what you're gonna say
所以這是這個你要說
Pre-Medication Genetic Screening to Help After Medication
用藥之前的基因篩檢來幫助用藥之後
to decide whether to prevent
來決定能不能預防
allergic reaction after use
用到之後過敏反應
This is also a very successful factor
這個也是一個很成功的要素
no knowledge at all
一點學問都沒有
But we only need the patient to wait two days
可是我們只要病人等兩天
you can talk to him
就可以跟他講
you can eat you can't eat
你可以吃 你不能吃
It is also a very successful requirement
這也是一個很成功的要件
The third
第三個
alternative medicine
替代用藥
suppose
假設
Check it out and say you can't eat it
檢查出來說你不能吃
what to do
那怎麼辦
No way, good way, you know the pain at home
沒辦 良辦 你知道的家裡那個痛
then why should i check
那我幹嘛要檢查
You also have a medicine called Actonative medicine
你還要有一個叫做Actonative medicine
You have to find another way to go
你要有其他的方法來走啊
you have to tell people
你要跟人家講說
assume you are positive
假設你是陽性
Suppose you want to change the medicine
假設你要換藥的話
what should you do
你應該怎麼辦
assuming it's useless
假設一點用都沒有
Then why do people want to do personalized medicine?
那人家幹嘛要做個人化醫學啊
so this stuff sounds uneducated
所以這些東西聽起來沒有什麼學問
but it is
可是就是
Our research shows that
我們這邊研究展示的說
If you really want to do personalized medicine
個人化醫學你真的要做的話
You need to be able to cooperate with the whole environment
你除了整個大環境要能夠配合之外
You have to consider these seem not very knowledgeable
你要考慮這些看起來沒有很大的學問
This is called the editor over there
這個就是叫做那邊編輯寫的
To a very appropriate called proper clinical setting
要一個很適當的叫做 proper clinical setting
appropriate clinical configuration
要很適當的臨床的配置
This clinical configuration includes the whole country and the whole environment
這臨床的配置包括整個國家整個環境
Public health and clinical standards can match
公共衛生跟臨床水準能夠配合
And how strong is the relationship between the disease itself and the gene?
以及這個病本身到底跟這個基因的關係有多強
and the relationships just mentioned
以及剛才提到的這些關係
So this is the third step of what we call personalized medicine here
所以這就是我們這裡提到的個人化醫學的第三個步驟
That is, you left with relevant basic evidence.
就是你走了有了相關基礎證據
if you really want to do it
你真的要去做的話
You have to take into account positive inhibitory values, negative inhibitory values
你要考慮到陽性抑熱值 陰性抑熱值
You also need to consider other allergic reactions caused by this disease
你還要考慮到這個病所引起的其他過敏反應
What to do about your rash, the clinically feasible approach
你紅疹會怎麼辦 臨床的可行徑
Can the patient wait for two days?
病人能等嗎 兩天可以等
Probably can't wait for two weeks, and check it out
兩個禮拜大概不能等 以及檢驗好做嗎
That is to say, our research
就是說我們這個研究
Our inspection department sometimes says it is too complicated
我們這個檢驗 檢驗科有時候說太複雜了
I don't want to do it. Maybe he strikes with you sometimes.
我不想做 他有時候跟你罷工也說不定
You do a good job of developing those test designs
你發展那些檢驗設計要好做
and the alternatives just mentioned
以及剛才講的替代方案
Is there an alternative? Suppose there is.
到底有沒有替代方案 假設有了
It's really about personalization.
真的本來就走到個人化一起來
So I can’t go back to the Hershiting I just talked about
所以回不 剛才講的Hershiting
nature has revealed that clue economics
自然已經透露那個線索經濟學
This sentence means
這句話就是說
We published it in the Sexy Together journal
我們那時候發表在性感一起來期刊
The best journal in the world We are very good in our hearts
全世界最好期刊 我們心裡面都很可以
Proud of our central PR city
很驕傲 那個我們中央的公關市
a press conference is about to be held
就要舉行記者招待會
because it can be a great sight
因為這可以大大的風光一番
As a result, the press conference, the reporter came
結果記者招待會 記者來了
Reported the next day, the first media said
第二天報導 有一個第一個媒體就說
This is a major breakthrough in personalized medicine, benefiting from these seven years
這是個人化醫學一大突破 把這七年得益
Because it is to let the foreign media say the same
因為是讓國外的媒體也這樣講
But everyone turned over
可是大家翻一翻
You go Google my name and you can find
你去用Google找我的名字 你可以發現
I was scolded badly by you
我被你拿罵得慘了
Because the Central News Agency said a word
因為中央社講了一句話
That sentence really puts us in a strong mood
那句話真的是讓我們心情很強
Don't miss the butterfly, what did he say?
別到蝴蝶,他句話講什麼?
called
叫做
For three yuan of medicine, you need to do a genetic screening for three yuan and three thousand yuan
三塊錢的藥,要做三塊三千塊的基因篩檢
During this period, we suddenly acted violently. Scientists cannot handle scientific matters.
這段我們忽然猛行,科學家不能夠執掌科學的事情
You have to take into account, economics
你要考慮到,經濟學啊
CBZ only costs 3 yuan for a medicine
CBZ一顆藥才三塊錢
You want health insurance, health insurance is now almost 1502 genetic screening
你要健保,健保現在幾乎1502的基因篩檢了
Check a 1502, health insurance costs almost three thousand dollars, is it worth it?
檢查一個1502,健保要幾乎三千塊錢,值得嗎?
Therefore, personalized medicine cannot
所以,個人化醫學不能夠
I am very proud that the dominant activity of personalized medicine is unreasonable
很得意,個人化醫學獨大活動就有天下無理
You have to think about the situation in a real society
你要想到,真的一個社會的情形
Can it be accepted in the end, so when we
到底能不能接受,因此我們當的時候
Of course I can't wait, the Central News Agency's Cheng Xiao can still be broken
當然恨不得吧,那個中央社的成小,還可以斷
In hindsight, it's because he made us think
後來事後想,就是因為他讓我們想到
Personalized medicine can't just be scientific research
個人化醫學不能夠只有科學研究啊
Not only, as I just said, pharmacoeconomics should be taken into consideration
不能夠只有,剛剛講了要考慮到藥物經濟學
Therefore, we are not experts in pharmacoeconomics
因此,我們不是藥物經濟學的專家
Let's do the math
就稍微來算一算說
In the past few years
到底這幾年來
How is the use of CBZ in Taiwan?
CBZ在台灣用的情形怎麼樣
you can find
你可以發現
You see these curves
大家看到這幾條曲線
Dark blue and light blue are the same
深藍跟淺藍都是一樣
is that you found that from 2002 to 2008
就是你發現從2002年到2008年
CBZ usage actually declined
CBZ的用量事實上是下降的
you think
你心裡想
such an effective medicine
那麼有效的一顆藥
So cheap, a painkiller that costs 3 yuan is so cheap
那麼便宜一顆加三塊錢的止痛藥那麼便宜
It's the cheapest of all medicines
這在所有的藥當中很便宜
Why is it getting lower and lower
為什麼越來越下降
The incidence of that Steven Jones is actually getting higher and higher
導致那個Steven Jones的發生率事實上是越來越高的
Why
為什麼
After 2004, we did not just talk about
2004年之後我們我們剛剛不是講
Academician Chen and the others published in the famous Nature in 2004 that
陳院士他們在2004年在有名的nature發表說
1502 is after CBZ what caused Steven Jones
1502是CBZ導致Steven Jones的原因之後
Everyone dare not prescribe that medicine
大家不敢開那顆藥
So after 2004
所以2004年之後
CBZ has been falling
CBZ就一直下降
you don't want to be that
你不要是那個
It means you don't want that or that
等於是你不要那個那個
The flower of the tight pen said that I have a very good test
緊筆之花說我有很好的test
I'm telling you now that I don't do tests at all
現在在跟你講我根本不要做test
I just need to change the medicine.
我根本換藥就好了嘛
What do you have to worry about 1502
你根本要擔心什麼1502
Just change your medicine
你乾脆就換一顆藥
So it prompts us to think about one thing
因此就促使我們來想一件事情
that's where we come to see
就是我們來看這裡
think of one thing is to say
想一件事情就是說
Then we have to actually calculate
那我們要真的計算
In the end personalized medicine is really used in a society
到底個人化醫學真的用在一個社會
one country
一個國家
What about medical costs
到底對於醫療成本
How much does it affect
到底它的影響有多大
that's a good point to say
那很好的一點就是說
1502, Steve Johnson
1502, Steve Johnson
It is mentioned in foreign textbooks one day
就是國外教科書一日提到
This is the best example
這是最好的一個例子
because of trigeminal neuralgia
因為在邊間跟三叉神經痛
are two different situations
是兩種不一樣的情況
In addition to CVD
邊間目前除了CVD之外
there is another medicine
還有另外一顆藥
It is neurotic, gupmenting
就是neurotic, gupmenting
It's a very good medicine
是非常好的一顆藥
gupmenting is a bit of Steve Johnson's part
gupmenting是一點 Steve Johnson的部位
CVD is what you have to worry about is it 1502
CVD就是你要擔心是不是1502
So suppose a patient in the margin
所以假設一個邊間的病人
If he wants to eat CVD
他要吃CVD的話
in accordance with current standard practice
依照現在的標準做法
you have to do it first
你要先做
You have to spend 3,000 yuan for genetic screening first
你要先花3000塊錢去做基因篩檢
Assuming it is a network
假設是network的話
You can rest assured to eat CVD
你就放心的去吃CVD
Because BZ is very cheap, it only costs three yuan a day
BZ因為很便宜,一天一顆才三塊錢
The annual drug fee is 2300 yuan
一年的藥費是2300塊
So 2300 plus 3000, one year we don't care
所以2300加3000,一年我們不管說
In fact, patients with epilepsy can't just watch for a year
事實上癲癲的病人不能夠只看一年
Epilepsy patients move up because they eat for a long time
癲癲的病人動漲是吃很久
So assuming it's CBZ plus that 1502 genetic screening
所以假設是CBZ加上那個1502基因篩檢
It costs 5300 yuan a year
一年花5300塊錢
But some people say I just change the medicine
可是有些人說我乾脆換藥就好了
why do i take this risk
我乾嘛還冒這個危險
Neurotin costs 11 yuan a piece
Neurotin一顆要11塊錢
It costs 10,000 yuan a year to eat
吃一年要1萬塊錢
10,000 to 5300 which one is calculated
1萬比5300哪一個核算
Of course this calculation
當然這個核算
so this is
所以這個就是
execute us, we are very grateful to that miss chen
處死我們,我們很感謝那位陳小姐
help us tell you
幫助我們跟大家講
Although you said three thousand dollars
說雖然你說三千塊錢
Three dollars will cost 3,000 dollars for a genetic screening
三塊錢要做三千塊錢的基因篩檢
it sounds unreasonable
聽起來好像很不合理
But in the long run
可是就長遠來看
Epilepsy patients have to take medicine for a lifetime
癲癲的病人要吃一輩子的藥
even if you change the medicine
即使你換藥的話
very expensive
很貴啊
certainly
當然
We don't deny assuming you have money and are willing to pay for it
我們不否認假設你有錢願意自費
Willing to spend 10,000 yuan a year
願意花一年花一萬塊錢
then you really are your business
那你真的是你的事
But considering a country
可是就一個國家的考量的話
2,0003 plus 3,000
2,0003加3,000
And genetic screening only needs to be done once
而且基因篩檢只要做一次
Because whether we are who or not in our whole life is 1502
因為我們一輩子到底是不是誰是1502
If you check once you do it
一做一次就檢查的話
That will have a lifetime impact
那就一輩子的影響
It is to sign a document 2,0003 2,0003 2,0003
就是顛簽一支資料2,0003 2,0003 2,0003
This is 10,000 plus 10,000 plus 10,000
這是1萬加1萬加1萬
In the long run, it seems that this is relatively accounting.
長期看起來這個還是比較核算
This is a case of subversion
這是顛簽的情形
Indeed, from the point of view of the subverted patients
的確就顛簽的病人來看
Although there are good alternatives to
雖然顛簽有很好的替代用藥
Can not eat CBZ
可以不要吃CBZ
Immediately switch to alternative medicine
馬上換替代用藥
But as things stand now
可是到現在的情況來看
Several common alternative medicines
幾種常見的替代用藥
There is no accounting from CBZ
沒有一種起CBZ來的核算
should say so
應該這麼講
There is no calculation other than CBZ plus genetic screening
沒有一種比CBZ加上基因篩檢來的核算
This is a case of subversion
這是顛簽的情形
the second
第二個
Three margins
三差成績
Didn't we just talk
我們剛剛不是講說
Taiwan does have 50% of the people
台灣的確有50%的人
It's because of stacking pain and three plus scores
是因為疊痛三加成績
So we still eat CBZ
所以我們還吃CBZ
But another story happened
可是另外的故事產生了
for trigeminal neuralgia
對於三叉神經痛而言
CBG is the front line
CBG是第一線
and there is no alternative
而且沒有替代用藥
won't be like that
不會像剛才那個
There is copamenting in that side
那個邊間還有copamenting
trigeminal neuralgia
可以用三叉神經痛
CBG is the best medicine
CBG是最好的藥
so there is no alternative
因此沒有什麼替代方案了
you have to think
你就要想
Another way to think about talking to people
另外一個方式來想跟人話一起
just think
就要想
How much does it cost me to prevent a patient
我預防一個病人要花多少錢
and i don't prevent
以及我不預防
I let him go free
我讓他去放生
I use ex post compensation
我用事後的救濟事後的賠償
How much do you have to pay
到底要賠多少錢
we really count
我們就真的來算
Steven Johnson caused by CBG
就CBG所引起的Steven Johnson
The incidence rate is about 0.24%
發生率大概0.24%
According to the data we have just demonstrated
依照我們剛才實證的資料
can be calculated
可以算得出來
So let's say 1000 patients
所以假設是1000個病人
If multiplied by 0.24%
乘以0.24%的話
1000 are CBG's
1000個是CBG的
There will probably be two Steven Johnsons
大概會有兩個Steven Johnson
So 1,000 people on pills
所以1000個吃藥的人
there will be two steven johnson
會有兩個Steven Johnson
Those 1,000 people multiplied by the
那1000個人乘以剛剛講
It costs 3,000 yuan to do a screening
做一次篩檢要3000塊
3000 times 1000
3000乘以1000
is 3 million
就是300萬
3 million divided by two patients
300萬除以兩個病人
3 million divided by 2
300萬除以2
That's 1.5 million
就是150萬
he means to say
他的意思就是說
You want to prevent a trigeminal neuralgia
你要預防一個三叉神經痛
People who eat CBG and get Steven Johnson
吃CBG得Steven Johnson的人
You prevent a Steven Johnson on average
你平均預防一個Steven Johnson
it will cost 1.5 million
要花150萬
Then suppose I don't prevent
那假設我不預防
that's too expensive
那太貴了
shall we accompany
我們來陪嘛
Let's do the math here
我們就這來算算看
Vital Relief Foundation
依據要害救濟基金會
Steven Johnson has several conditions
Steven Johnson有幾種狀況
no sequelae
沒有後遺症
Some people have very serious sequelae
有的人是很嚴重的後遺症
eyes will go blind
眼睛都會瞎掉
Of course some people will die
那當然有些人會不幸往生
The vast majority of Steven Johnson are very serious
絕大部分Steven Johnson非常嚴重
But 92% of people
可是92%的人
In the end, the skin will be healed after half a year
到最後就是皮膚半年之後好了
For treating a Steven Johnson
對於治療一個Steven Johnson
Almost 400,000 in health insurance
健保幾乎40萬
that for those who are blind
那對於那些眼睛瞎掉
Only 0.2%
只有0.2%
Health insurance almost 1 million
健保幾乎100萬
5.26% for the unlucky
對於不幸往生的5.26%
Taiwan underground
台灣地下
How much is a human life worth?
一個人人命值多少錢
two million
兩百萬
So you multiply 400,000 by 0.29
所以你把40萬乘以0.29
1 million times 0.02
100萬乘以0.02
2 million times 0.05
200萬乘以0.05
count up
算起來
Average to pay
平均去賠
You don't do any fund screening
你不做任何基金篩檢
you pay on average
你平均去賠
A Patient of Stephen Ginger
一個史蒂芬姜省的病人
The state will spend 500,000
國家要花50萬
1.5 million vs. 500,000
150萬比50萬
which one compares
哪一個比較核算
Of course 500,000 accounting
當然50萬核算
but this thing
可是這個東西
At the Department of Health
當年在衛生署
The Drug Harm Relief Foundation
那個藥害救濟基金會
Indeed, some teachers of medical economics say
的確有些醫療經濟學的老師說
you pay
你賠就好嘛
1.5 million vs. 500,000
150萬比50萬
Of course this calculation
當然這個核算
But then I thought of what example
可是那時候我想到是什麼例子
I think it is an example that you often see in newspapers
我想到是大家常常在報紙上看到的一個例子
kill the driver
殺死車司機
I'd rather kill someone
寧可把一個人撞死
I don't want to put a person
也不願意把一個人
crippled
撞得殘廢
Isn't that what it looks like?
這起不就是這樣子嗎
I think you just let happen
我看你乾脆就讓發生好你一個
It's fine for the country to pay
國家去賠就好了
Because the compensation is only 500,000
因為賠只要50萬啊
You need 1.5 million to prevent one
你預防一個要150萬
Both are 1 million
兩者也100萬啊
Because why is there such a difference
因為為什麼會有這種差別
because we didn't count a single person
因為我們沒有計算一個人
After being disabled
殘廢之後
We don't count after a person dies
我們沒有計算一個人死了之後
his life's loss
他到底一輩子的損失
In the current medical economics, there is no formula
在目前的醫療經濟學是沒有公式算的
the second
第二個
Our society in Taiwan
我們台灣這個社會
Can this really be allowed to happen?
真的能夠容許這件事情發生嗎
can really say
能真能夠容許說
Then once something happens to compensate
那一旦一件事情發生來賠
Then don't come and do precautions in advance
然後不來做事先的預防
Some doctors even say
甚至有些醫師講
say in terms of medical standards
說就醫療的準則而言
What is one thing that can be prevented and not prevented
一件事情可以預防而不去預防是什麼
illegal
違法的
This does not mean that it can be prevented and cannot be prevented
這就起不就是可以預防不能夠預防
Now that Academia Sinica is very old
現在那個中研院已經很老了
Study says 1502 has good checks
研究說1502有很好的檢查
Come for 1502 genetic screening
來做1502基因篩檢
But why should we consider
可是我們為什麼要考慮到
Is it ethically reasonable?
倫理上面是不是很合理
and social affordability
以及社會的負擔能力啊
we really this society
我們真的這個社會
Really only care about the difference between 1.5 million and 500,000
真的只在乎150萬跟50萬的差別
certainly
當然
we are a scholar
我們是一個學者
It's the Central Asian crowd garden. How can we
是中亞人群園當說我們怎麼可以
Taiwan is so developed
我們台灣那麼樣發達
How can you care about 1 million
怎麼會在乎100萬
But Vice President Chen used to be the Director of Health
可是像陳副院長以前當過衛生署長
It's different when he sees here
他看到這裡就不一樣了
Because every disease is like this
因為什麼每一個病都是這樣
You have to choose breast cancer and tell you
你要選擇乳癌也跟你講說
The 800,000 yuan for Heshan disease is also worth spending
那個荷山病80萬也值得花
When that lung cancer, that Aresa
那個肺癌的時候那個Aresa
Your health insurance is so much money
你健保就是那麼多錢
So what is the use of limited resources to treat
那到底是要把那個有限的資源去治療
Heart to Pusture Breast Cancer Patient
Heart to Pusture 乳癌病人
Or to prevent a CBG
還是要來預防一個CBG
caused by steven johnson
所引起的Steven Johnson
that's a hard choice
那就是很難的抉擇
so this thing has no answer
所以這個東西沒有答案
This thing just prompts us to think carefully
這個東西只是促使我們好好地來思考說
Personalized medicine is really coming to an end
個人化醫學真的走到最後
When you really have to calculate medical costs
你真的要算醫療成本的時候
Your country has to choose to say
你國家就要選擇說
where are you going to put your resources
你要把你的資源放在哪裡
So this Steven Johnson with
所以這個Steven Johnson跟
The relationship between 1502 and CBG
跟那個1502跟CBG的關係
is a very good example from a textbook
是一個非常好的一個教科出的例子
Find related from the beginning
從開始找相關
Take our new person to basic research
到基礎研究帶我們那個新一個人去
So it depends on how to do it clinically to be effective
所以才看臨床上怎麼做才能夠有效
and being a reporter we ignore
以及做一個我們忽略被那個記者
HK's so-called medical economics
HK所謂的醫療經濟學
So this is a really good example
所以這是一個非常好的例子
Tell us how personalized medicine should be done
告訴我們說個人化醫學應該怎麼做
Finally, tell us that is personalized medicine
最後告訴我們就是個人化醫學
is to take into account the differences from person to person
就是以考慮到人跟人的差異
But the difference between this person
可是這個人跟人的差異
Finally, what we just said
最後就是我們剛剛講的
The 1502 and CBZ we just mentioned
我們剛才提到的1502跟CBZ
caused by steven johnson
所引起的Steven Johnson
That's a strong hurdle that's monofactorial
那是一個很強的傷關是單因子
is now what we encounter
是現在我們碰到的是什麼
Hypertension Diabetes Cancer Cardiolipidemia
高血壓 糖尿病 癌症 心臟缺乏脂病
and the occurrence of disease
而且是疾病的發生
Disease treatment is simple
疾病的治療很單純
You can give different drugs according to different patients
你可以依據不同的病人給不同藥
but what happens
可是發生怎麼辦
That is to say
也就是說
Let me take that as an example of a study by Vice President Chen.
我拿那個也是陳副院長的一個研究來講
That's the study just now
就是剛才那篇研究
Their study looked at the liver function of a person at the same time
他們這篇研究有同時看一個人肝功能好壞
People with poorer liver function
肝功能越差的人
His one has a higher risk of liver cancer
他的那個得肝癌危險性越高
or according to just said
或者是依據剛才講
Qixing should research the virus
七星該研病毒的
Assuming that it belongs to the first type of management
假設是屬於第一種經營型的高
It is equivalent to adding three factors into the
等於是把三個因素加進來
Just mentioned three factors
三個因素就剛剛講
High or low viral load
病毒量高低
Then liver function is good or bad
然後肝功能好壞
And in the end HCV belongs to
以及到底HCV是屬於
bad type or good type
不好型還是好型
Six situations are better than just one situation
六種情形比剛才一種情形
More accurate prediction of a person's risk of liver cancer
更能精準預估一個人的肝癌危險性
This means that
這就是說
for complex diseases
對於複雜疾病而言
Nothing like 1502 and CBG caused
沒有像1502跟CBG所引起的
Steven Johnson
Steven Johnson
Because it is a single cause
因為是單病因
But for liver cancer
可是對肝癌
Liver cancer caused by type C liver cancer
C型肝癌引起的肝癌而言
you have to take into account besides you
你還要除了你還要考慮到
Beyond the highs and lows of type C liver cancer
C型肝癌的高低之外
You have to consider the quality of liver function
你要考慮到肝功能的好壞
you have to consider someone
你還要考慮到一個人
In the end, type C liver cancer belongs to the strong and the weak
到底C型肝癌是屬於強跟弱
Therefore, the concept
因此再把這個概念
It is used in the treatment of the five cancers we just talked about
用在我們剛才講五癌的治療
We just said that the assumption is
我們剛才講假設是
Her to Pasitidon
Her to Pasitidon
Can give him and setting
可以給他和setting
Here is another example
這裡舉的是另外一個例子
Supposed to be Her to Pasitidon
假設是Her to Pasitidon
Can two medicines be given? One is Leftal Role
可以給兩種藥嗎?一種是Leftal Role
One is that Tamazifen
一個是那個Tamazifen
I didn’t just say that Leftal Role can cause serious osteoporosis
剛才不是講Leftal Role會引起很嚴重的骨質疏鬆
So what is the way a person can decide to say
那有什麼樣的方法能夠讓一個人決定說
Should I give Leftal Role or Tamazifen
到底我應該給Leftal Role還是給Tamazifen
Then those of us who study breast cancer discovered one of the genes
那我們研究乳癌的人就發現其中一個基因
That gene is called CYP2D6
那個基因就是叫做CYP2D6
Why? The Tamazifen that I ate
為什麼?吃下去的那顆Tamazifen
It's not about grabbing the position directly.
並不是直接就會去搶位置
But through the activation of the gene CYP2D6
而是要藉由CYP2D6這個基因的活化
Thus a concept arises
因此一個概念就產生
Suppose my CYP2D6 is very strong
假設我的CYP2D6是屬於很強的話
Then I'll go eat Tamazifen
那我趕快去吃Tamazifen
if i'm weak
假設我是很弱的話
Just go and eat this trick obediently with peace of mind
乾脆就安心的去乖乖的來吃這招
Really long track looks like
真的長期的追蹤看起來
2008 really looked like this
2008年看起來的確是這樣子
What to track after 5 years
追蹤什麼到了5年之後
All kinds are breast cancer survival
種種就是乳癌的存活力
You can find that two of them survive the best
你可發現其中有兩種存活力最好
The top group is gray and this line is what I just said
最上面的組就是灰色的這條線就是剛才講的
The group that ate meat had the best survival rate
吃肉這組存活率最好
I don't need to talk about it just now
這不用我講剛才講
but it has side effects
可是它副作用大
but you found out
可是你有發現
there's another set that's as good as it
其中有另外一組跟它一樣好
That group of dots is this group
那一組打點的這組就是
Tama 7
Tama 7
Plus CYB2D6 is part of
再加上CYB2D6是屬於
Mom and Dad give good words
爸爸媽媽都給好型的話
Its survival rate is almost as good as that meat
它的存活率幾乎跟那種肉一樣好
Conversely which group is the worst
反之哪一組最差
That's Tama 7
就是Tama 7
Or if you add CYB2D6 and only bet on changing the epidemic situation
或再加上CYB2D6都只賭一變疫情的話
That is to say, eating equals to no effect
也就是說吃得等於沒效
So the other one just mentioned
所以另外一個剛才講的
You have to decide what a patient wants to eat
你要決定一個病人到底要吃
Lovers and love kings still grab the position
情者又情王還是搶位置這一招
Then do CYB2D6 gene screening first
那就先做CYB2D6基因篩檢
If it is positive
假設是陽性的話
you don't go to that to endure
你就不要去那個忍受
that very complicated pause syndrome
那個很複雜的停頓症候群
you go eat one cheap and effective
你去吃一個又便宜又有效
heavy duty medicine
負重又小的藥
That hypothesis is CYB2D6
那假設是CYB2D6
If it belongs to the bad genotype
是屬於不好的基因型的話
Then come and eat this obediently
那你乖乖的來吃這個
This is also a contribution of personalized medicine
這也是個人化醫學的一個貢獻
the same reason
同樣的道理
Progressive treatment
即便的發生進展治療
from just now
從剛才那個
Just come with the example of bacterial hepatitis virus
剛來跟細菌肝炎病毒的例子
or Liptoid CYB2D6
或者是Liptoid CYB2D6
Or the Tamasibin example
或者是Tamasibin例子
Tell us about progressing treatment
告訴我們說發生進展治療
to use more indicators
要用更多的指標
Some of these indicators are external factors
這些指標有的是外界的因素
For example, is bacterial hepatitis virus strong or weak?
譬如說到底細菌肝炎病毒是強勤還是弱勤
and factors within governance
以及治理內部的因素
Is liver function good or bad?
肝功能到底是好還是不好
Or is my CYB2D6 a strong worker or a weak worker?
或者是我的CYB2D6是屬於強勤還是弱勤
can determine the occurrence of disease
可以來決定疾病的發生
Disease progression and disease treatment
疾病的進展以及疾病的治療
this is what we're talking about
這個就是我們講的
Customized Personalized Medicine
客製化的個人化醫學
But it's really going to get to the point we imagined.
可是真的要走到我們想像當中的那個地步
We use this picture to show you Chinese painting at the beginning
我們用這個圖一開始給大家看國畫
Finally, let’s look at the famous Spanish Road No.
最後就是來看有名的西班牙道號
Called Diago Velasquez
叫做Diago Velasquez
A picture he drew is called the picture of ladies and gentlemen.
他畫的一幅圖就是叫做士女圖
What is the picture of ladies and gentlemen?
什麼士女圖呢
He is Ukishi Taxi
他就是浮世的士
he painted little spanish princesses
他畫西班牙的小公主
There is a group of ladies and gentlemen next to him
他旁邊有一群士女
Also includes things like come to make him laugh
還包括諸如來動他笑
And the dog keeps coming by his side
還一直狗來在他旁邊
Just this little Spanish princess to make him laugh
就這個西班牙小公主來逗他笑
these people serve him
這些人服侍他
That's why it's called the picture of the maid
所以這幅才叫侍女圖
So what is Diego Velazquez painting
那Diago Vilazquez畫的是什麼
What he paints is what he is here is a sense of painting
他畫的是他這裡是一個畫感
Vilazquez even drew himself in it
Vilazquez甚至還把自己畫在裡面
Whose house is he drawing until the end guess
他在畫誰人家到最後猜
inside the mirror
鏡子裡面
The father and the queen are here
父王跟母后在這邊
He means that this picture drawn by Vilazquez is
他就是說 Vilazquez畫的這幅圖就是
The father and the queen stand in front of this
父王跟母后站在這前面
He was drawing his daughter bored beside him
他在畫他的那個女兒在旁邊無聊
Next to it is a group of maids to make him laugh
旁邊就是一群侍女來逗他笑
dog to accompany him
狗來陪他
The maid came to make him laugh
侍女來逗他笑
So this is Diago Vilazquez's version
所以這是Diago Vilazquez的版本
On the right is the B.Casso version
右邊就是B.Casso版本
Put the painting of the maid by Vilazquez
放 Vilazquez畫的侍女圖
where did you say the princess
你說公主在哪裡
princess is here
公主在這裡
The maid is probably this
侍女大概是這個
the dog is probably this
狗大概是這個
Then Vilazquez is a little unclear here
那Vilazquez這裡就有點不太清楚
I use this to mention
我用這個來給大家提到
1502 with diabetes
1502跟糖藥病
1502 and breast cancer
1502跟乳癌
1502 with lung cancer
1502跟肺癌的
As far as 1502 is black and white
就1502年黑百分明
Because as far as 1502 the relationship is strong
因為就1502年關係很強
Three genes, people are people, dogs are dogs
三基因 人是人 狗是狗
But the high blood that we generally care about
可是對我們一般關心的高血
Diabetes and cancer
糖尿病癌症的發生而言
Must-have version
必卡手版本
everyone contributes a little bit
每一個人貢獻一點點
That is to say
也就是說
in the past
就過去而言
one or two big genes
都是一兩個大基因
He decided to go east or west or west
他就決定要東就東 要西西就西
But the chronic diseases we often talk about
可是我們常講的慢性疾病
It's a bunch of little dick genes
是一大堆小蘿蘿基因
common combination
共同的組合
You're looking for the disease impact of large genes
你要找大基因的疾病影響
That's like 1502 to decide
那就像1502來決定
State 1 caused by CPG
CPG所引起的State 1
well done
很好做
Great for Personalized Medicine
很好做個人化醫學
Because of the single factor relationship and
因為單因子關係又
But suppose we're talking about chronic diseases
可是假設我們講的慢性疾病
If it's a combination of a lot of little dick genes
是一大堆小蘿蘿基因的組合的話
How much should it be reduced
那要減它幾個
Is it enough to subtract five? Is ten enough?
減它五個夠不夠 十個夠不夠
thirty is enough
三十個夠不夠
Take the example of breast cancer that I am most familiar with
拿我最熟悉的乳癌的例子來講
where are the benefits
好處在哪裡
good thing is to say
好處的就是說
Thanks to medical scientists and
得利於醫學家以及
technologist progress
科技學家進步
They develop some biochips
他們發展一些生物晶片
Capable of whole-genome scanning
能夠進行全基因體的掃描
It is equivalent to saying that a 1502 should be checked before
等於是說以前要檢查一個 1502
3 hours or 3 days
3小時或3天
But the one at Academia Sinica is called the National Genotyping Center
可是中央研究院的那個叫做國家基因定型中心
He can check 500,000 genetic markers in one morning
他一個早上就可以檢查50萬個基因位檢
In this way, it can be considered at the same time
那這樣子就能夠同時的考慮到
The effect of a large number of small cages
一大堆小籠籠的影響
two aspects
二方面
used to be expensive to make
以前做起來很貴
What now
現在呢
Now it's time to advertise our national genotype
現在就是替我們國家基因型做個廣告
Assuming that the whole genome scans 600,000 positions
假設全基因體掃60萬個位置
We say that there are 3 billion genomes
我們講全部基因體有30億
How much does it cost to make a 3 billion
做一個30億要多少錢
In fact it is not expensive
事實上也不貴
I heard that Taiwanese people in that country and Wang Jianmin did it
聽說那個國台民跟王建民就做了
A person is 300,000
一個人就是個30萬
300,000 is not expensive
30萬你說不貴
Of course expensive
當然貴
But 300,000 can take you 3 billion
可是30萬能夠把你30億個
Re-read that genetic locus
那個基因位點都重新讀一遍
Do you say it's expensive?
你說貴不貴
not expensive
不貴啊
not bad
還好啊
The 300,000 is slightly used for the provincial branch
這30萬稍微那個省支解用
That one or two years can be responsible
那個一兩年就可以負責
Not to mention, suppose you said genetic typing
更何況 假設你說基因定型
It only costs 4,000 yuan per person. What is genetic typing?
一個人只要4000塊 什麼叫基因定型
That is to say, you have a high-speed rail car
就是說 你一部高鐵車子
You don't need every passenger to ask him if he is
你不需要每一個旅客都問他說是不是
You just need to look at one person
你要只要看一個人就好嘛
It’s like you can do it with all high-speed trains
等於是 你可以全部高鐵類車來做
You can see a few representative
你可以看幾個代表性的
Just look at a few representative words
那只要看幾個代表性的話
Only 4000 yuan per person
一個人只要4000塊錢
4000 yuan in Taiwan
4000塊錢 在台灣而言
Probably everyone can afford it
大概大家都會出得起
So you want a personalized medicine
所以你要一個個人化醫學
On the one hand, technological advances
一方面因為技術的進步
On the other hand, because of the cost reduction
二方面因為那個成本的下降
lead to find this little dick gene now
導致現在找這種小蘿蘿基因
much more important than before
比以前就重要很多
Then the example of diabetes mellitus we just talked about
然後我們剛才講的那個糖藥病的例子
It's what you saw in the upper right corner just now
就是剛才大家右上角看到
Obese people more likely to develop diabetes
肥胖的人越容易得糖藥病
But in 2008
可是在2008年
Whole genome scanning
人家就藉由全基因理掃描
16 loci were found
找到了16個基因位點
As a result, the 16 loci
結果這個16個基因位點
Can find small differences in Datong
能夠在大同當中找到小異
why
為什麼呢
The horizontal axis is a person's obesity index
就橫軸就是一個人肥胖指數
Obese people are more likely to develop diabetes
越胖的人越容易得糖藥病
Watch DJ getting more and more
看DJ越來越
But we just talked about genetic screening and humanized medicine
可是我們剛才講基因篩檢跟人化醫學
Definitely not saying obesity is important
絕對不是說肥胖重要
still important
照樣很重要
The fatter you are, the easier it is to get obesity
越胖的越容易得胖胖病
but where is the point
可是重點在哪裡
The focus is to find the small differences in the great same
重點在大同當中找到小異
Under the same obesity index
在同樣這個肥胖指數之下
Plus 16 loci for genes
再加上16個基因的位點
The number of bad genes is 8, 9, and 10
壞基因數目8個9個10個
11 12
11個12個
The greater the number of bad genes, the higher the risk
壞基因數目越多越來危險性越高
So it is equal to the occurrence of diabetes
所以等於是對於糖尿病的發生
Traditional risk factors combined with genetic screening
傳統的危險因素配合上基因篩檢
can affect a person's risk of developing diabetes
能夠對一個人得糖尿病的危險性
make a more accurate assessment
做更精準的評估
Just now my Vice President Chen mentioned
剛才我那個陳副院長提到
My laboratory participated in the world's first
我實驗室就參與這個全世界第一個
so-called genome-wide breast cancer screening
所謂的全基因體的乳癌篩檢
Whole Genome
結果找到全基因體當中
The most important gene is called FGF2
最重要的一個基因就是叫做FGF2
It's in different labs all over the world
它在全世界不同的實驗室
The horizontal axis is the so-called risk
橫軸就是所謂的危險性
Different laboratories around the world
全世界不同的實驗室
Including my laboratory at Academia Sinica
包括我在中央研究院的實驗室
Abbreviated as BCST is Bress Cancer Study
簡稱叫做BCST就是Bress Cancer Study
in the land of Taiwan
在大地臺灣
It is said that this FGF8 degree assumption is not good to carry out
都說這個FGF8度假設是不好的進行的話
It is 1.3 times more dangerous
它危險性增加1.3倍
Everyone says it's taller than one
大家都說它比一高
but please pay attention
可是請大家注意
1.3 is not 13 is not 130
1.3不是13不是130
How much was Steven Johnson just now? More than 1300
剛才Steven Johnson是多少?1300多
This is the so-called Xiaorouluo gene
這個就是所謂的小柔邏基因
more complex disease
越複雜的疾病
you have to explain the occurrence of the disease
你要解釋疾病發生的話
It's just a combination of a lot of Xiao Rouluo genes.
就是一大堆小柔邏基因共同的組合
So for these little soft genes
因此對於這些小柔邏基因
How to use it in personalized medicine
如何用在個人化醫學
There are many different controversies at present
就有很多目前不同的爭議產生
some people say
有些人說
Because of the advancement of technology
因為現在技術的進步
I can reduce the cost of technological progress
我可以進行技術的進步成本的下降
I can put all these things in health insurance later
我可以以後把這些東西都納入健保
that way you can afford it
那這樣子就可以負擔得起
but some people can say
可是有些人可以說
This little Rourou gene is only 1.3 times
這個小柔邏基因只有1.3倍
1.3 times the words
1.3倍的話
So how much can it contribute?
那到底能有多大的貢獻呢?
that's in our breasts
那在我們乳
Because it has the most genetic screening sites in the world
因為是全世界做基因篩點最多的
so would like to say
因此就會想說
Can we take the whole genetic competition just now?
能不能把剛才我們進行全基因比賽
The most important thing about the name of the station is the first place, what AGR
台名最重要的是第一名什麼AGR
Can we make better predictions about diseases?
排下來能夠對於疾病做更好的預測呢
His answer is here
他的答案在這裡
Just in industry last year
就是在工業去年
It is also the world's most famous Journal of New Geology
就是也是全世界最有名的新隔蘭學雜誌
Use the medical model to tell us that
用醫學的model告訴我們說
Suppose he uses a very complicated statistical model, I can't even understand it
假設他用很複雜的統計model 我都看不懂
He said ten points
他就說十個位點
The ten loci with less global gene power
全基因力少的那種十個位點
In addition, did you have any children just now?
再加上剛才講有沒有生小孩啊
See if you can predict
看看說能不能夠預測
The case of a girl suffering from five cancers
對一個女生得五癌的情形
Can we make better predictions
能不能做更好的預測
two conclusions
兩個結論
The first conclusion is quite pessimistic
第一個結論是蠻悲觀的
what is the first conclusion
第一個結論是什麼
Called Gail plus Sneed equals Gail
叫做Gail加Sneed等於Gail
What is Gail
Gail就是什麼
You go to the website of the National Health Bureau
你去上國健局網站
Gailmodel is based on traditional risk factors
Gailmodel就是依據傳統的危險因素
To assess how likely a girl is to have five cancers
來評估一個女生到底有多大的機率得五癌
traditional risk factors
傳統的危險因素
Plus genetic screening for ten loci
加上十個位點的基因篩檢
The predictability that can be equal to Gail
所能夠的預期性等於Gail
what is that
那等於是什麼
Cooperating with genetic screening is one point
配合基因篩檢是一點
so far
就目前為止
Suppose you only do ten
假設你只做十個
traditional risk factors
跟傳統危險因素
Predictions for Female Breast Cancer
對於女性乳癌的預測
not much help
沒有什麼太大幫忙
The pessimistic side What is the optimistic side?
悲觀面 樂觀面是什麼?
Suppose you only do ten positions
假設你只做十個位點
You get the same predictability as Gale
你得到的預測性跟Gale一樣
This is the optimistic side why?
這個就是樂觀面 為什麼?
Everyone assumes that they have done Gale
大家假設是有做過Gale的話
He asked you, how old are you?
他就問你說 請問你出經幾歲來
Just because I don't understand
就想 因為我想不懂
Is it 11 years old? 12 years old or 13 years old?
是11歲呢 12歲還是13歲
Can not remember
想不起來
Traditional risk factors rely on recall
傳統的危險因素都要靠回憶
Not very accurate, but the screening of genetic loci is very accurate
不太準 可是做基因位點的篩檢很準
A is AP is B
A就是AP就是B
A concept learned from the words of Gale just now
一個用剛才Gale的話一學的概念
You use a more accurate method
你用一個比較準的方法
compared with an inaccurate method
跟一個比較不太準的方法
Both seem to have similar risk assessments
兩者看起來對危險性的評估是差不多的
but so far
可是就目前為止
Assuming you only do ten
假設你只做十個的話
Probably the contribution is very limited
大概貢獻是非常的有限
The last question is
最後一個問題就是
Here is a list of the whole genome physiology scans
這裡就是列出全基因理掃描當中
Me and my friends abroad
我跟我那些國外的朋友
You can see that most of them are white
大家可以看到絕大部分都是白人
overwhelmingly white
絕大部分都是白人
All European countries and U.S. dollars
都是歐洲國家以及美金
Our group ranks the top ten for breast cancer in the world
我們這個團體所以以全世界的乳癌排出前十名
The top ten starts from the first place, what HG's vomit
前十名就是從第一名開始什麼 HG的把吐啊
Then I write red to represent that these ten are very important
那我寫紅色代表說這十個都很重要
My purpose is not to memorize this number for everyone.
我這個目的不是給大家記這個數字
where is the point
重點在哪裡
assuming only us asians
假設只看我們亞洲人
That's us Taiwanese
就是我們台灣人
Among the ten, the only important one is this
這十名當中重要的只有這個
top two
前兩名
In other words, personalized medicine even if everyone has done a full-body scan
也就是說個人化醫學即使大家做過全機力掃描
There are also his characteristics among different races.
不同種族之間還有他的特性啊
that is mentioned here
也就是這邊提到的
For example, here's another breast cancer researcher
例如說這裡是另外一個乳癌研究人們
We are also invited to participate
也是邀請我們參加
Even we Asians have formed an Asian alliance
就是我們亞洲人自己也組了一個亞洲聯盟
Find friends in Shanghai
就發現就找上海的朋友
Friends of Tianjin Friends of Nanjin
天津的朋友 南津的朋友
Taiwan is our Hong Kong
台灣就是我們香港
One locus found in chromosome 6 is particularly important
所發現在六號染涉體一個位點特別重要
This is a representative of invalid
這就是一代表沒效
More than one is effective
一以上就代表效
But you can see that this position is common in Japanese
可是你看這個位點在日本人就會一
we are here
我們這裡是一
they will get closer
他們就會越靠近一
Then at the white man, almost next to E
然後在白人 幾乎在伊的旁邊
Black people change color on pigs and sheep
黑人就豬羊變色
he means to say
他的意思就是說
between different races
不同種族之間
The same point has different importance
同樣一點的重要性就不一樣
therefore
因此
And finally this
最後就是這個
personalized medicine
個人化醫學
We really want to personalize medicine
我們真的要做個人化醫學
on the one hand
一方面
Need more political evidence
要有更多時政的證據
It means that every case must be considered, starting from the first step
就是要有每一個case都要考慮到 剛才講的從第一步
What to look for evidence related to the basis
什麼要找相關基礎的證據
Can it be done clinically, can't be done by public health practitioners, and medical economics
臨床上能不能做得到 公共衛生師不能做得到 以及醫療經濟學
The first point
第一點
Second point
第二點
It's just that you have to think that now it's all a combination of Little Lolo's genes
就是你要想到現在都是小蘿羅基因的組合
Never again do you think that one or two big genes can determine
你再也不要想到說一兩個大基因就能夠決定
Even if all
即便全部
third point
第三點
between races
種族之間
Differences
有差異
The effect is
造成的影響就是
If you want to understand the influence of Little Lolo's genes
你要了解小蘿羅基因的影響的話
You want a large sample size
你要很大的樣本數
You need to understand the influence of different races
你要了解不同種族的影響
you want a different race
你要不同種族
Make his own personalized medicine basic information
做他自己的個人化醫學基本資料
So in the end it is
因此最後就是
Our Central Medical College started
我們中央醫學院開始了
biological database
生物資料庫
It was under the leadership of Vice President Chen that he aspired to be our president
就是在那個陳副院長領導志向我們院長
The instruction means that since we
指示就是說 那我們既然
Since personalized medicine is a future trend
既然個人化醫學是一個未來的趨勢
Since you need a large sample for personalized medicine
那你既然個人化醫學需要很大的樣本
Empirical data are specific to people of different races
實證的資料不同種族人物有特異性
then we'll build a biobank
那我們就建立一個生物資料庫
This is to help you find these empirical materials.
來為等於是幫大家去找這些實證的資料
Let the next generation
讓下一代
Let the next generation come back to find these empirical evidence
讓我們下一代再要來找這些實證的證據
When the polygenic influence
那個多基因的影響的時候
There is no need to track another five, ten, or twenty years
上也不需要再去追蹤個五年十年 二十年
So this is the one in our center
所以這個就是我們中央就那個
Our dean is trying his best to promote this left and right
我們院長極力在推動這個左右的
Taiwan biological database and biomarkers
台灣生物資料庫以及生物標誌
Dean Chen Wu is now leading the project
這個現在由陳務院長在領導這個計畫
Then I'll make a fool of myself tonight
那我今天晚上就耍誤到
Yes, it's late everyone, thank you all
對 大家很晚的時間 那謝謝大家
thanks a lot
很謝謝
This wonderful speech by our deputy director Chen Zhiqiang
我們陳志強副所長的這一個精采的演講
From the part of medicine to the part of humanities, social economics
他從醫學的部分到人文社會經濟學的這個
The whole involve to personalized medicine
整個involve到個人化醫學
a little late
時間有點晚
but we will allow you to ask a question or two
但是我們還容許大家問一兩個問題
Is there a very...
有沒有很...
The problem of not being able to go home today
今天不回不了家的問題
come please
來 請
that i have two questions
那個 我有兩個問題
One is that you have found 1502 and SBG
一個就是說你們已經找到1502跟SBG
then it is directly related
那麼就是直接的相關
So why is it only 5.8% in that positive predictive value
那為什麼在那個陽性預測值裡頭只有5.8%
This is the first question
這是第一個問題
The second question is to say
第二個問題是說
CBG is now used for that trigeminal neuralgia
CBG現在是用在那個三叉神經痛的
only drug of choice
唯一的選擇藥物
Then if after going through the disaster volume
那如果經過精災卷以後
It turned out that it was not suitable for this drug
結果又發現它是不適用這個藥物
But you said there is no alternative medicine
可是你說又沒有替代的藥物
What should we do at this time?
那這個時候要怎麼辦呢
The second question is a clinical question
第二個問題是臨床問題
As far as my clinician friend is concerned,
就我那個臨床醫師的朋友就是說
Suppose it is 1502
假設是1502的話
because of trigeminal neuralgia
因為三叉神經痛
We joke that the pain is bearable
我們開玩笑講痛可以忍受
He said you just have to bear it
他說你忍一忍就夠
So when...
所以當...
So far, the three-pronged dust has penetrated 1502 positive words
目前為止就三叉塵叮透1502 positive的話
In fact there is no medicine
事實上是沒有藥啦
Then usually everyone will make some comparisons
那通常大家都會開一些比較
less effective pain relievers
不太有效的止痛藥
Just eat like R-Spitling
像R-Spitling吃一吃就好了
is this
那這是不是
What if it doesn't work then?
那時候沒效怎麼辦
It didn't work and I cried for two days
沒效兩天就哭啦
That pain will go away
那痛就就消啦
But every day is different
可是天天不一樣
Every day is a lifetime thing
天天是一輩子的事情
So this is what you just mentioned
所以這一點就您剛才提到的
no alternative medicine
沒有替代用藥
What is genetic screening useful for?
基因篩檢有何用
suppose i know
假設我曉得說
What is that CIP2D6
那個什麼CIP2D6
The physical fitness of the doctor who treats the positive doctor is so poor
對陽性醫者的醫生體能那麼差
Then why am I doing genetic screening?
那我幹嘛做基因篩檢
so this has no answer
所以這個沒有答案
you are right
您講的一點都沒錯
no answer
沒有答案
This is what drives us
這個就是促使我們
many people say
就很多人講
You scientists are desperately trying to discover a bunch of agents
你科學家拼命發現一大堆劑
But really clinically
可是真的在臨床上
where is the contribution to public health
公共衛生的貢獻在哪裡
I'm sorry about this
這個很抱歉
we don't have an answer
我們沒有答案
so far
到目前為止就是
That put it mildly or because of some
那個說得一忍或者是因為一些
Just take the medicine that doesn't seem to be effective
看起來不太有效的藥就去吃吧
Anyway, the pain took two days to bear.
反正痛就是兩天就忍過去了
Then the first answer is to say
那回答到第一個就是說
why positive
為什麼陽性
Positive-negative predictive value so high
陽性陰性預測值那麼高
Positive negative predictive value so low
陽性陰性預測值那麼低
This responsible person is the head of this Liu Qing's graduate essay
這個負人長這劉慶畢業文長講
screening tool
篩檢工具
screening tool you are equal to
篩檢工具你等於是
Are you looking for false positives or false negatives
你要找到偽陽性還是偽陰性
your criteria you want your screening tools
你的標 你希望你的篩檢工具
Able to cut the masculine from the feminine
能夠把陽性跟陰性切得好好的
But there must be overlap between the two
可是兩者之間一定有重疊
some people will be fine with medicine
有些人吃藥會沒事
Some people take medicine
有些人吃藥會也是
Some people will be fine if they don't take medicine
有些人不吃藥也會有事
Then where do you cut the point?
那你到底切點也要切在哪裡
For example, what is called high blood?
譬如說什麼叫做高血啊
you can set it at 200 you can set it at 160
你可以定200 你可以定在160
you cut 160
你切160
Say 160 is a person with high blood pressure
就說160是高血壓的人
you should exercise more every day
你每天都要多運動
you'll catch a bunch
你會抓到一大堆
high blood pressure not high blood pressure
不是高血壓的高血壓
Conversely, suppose your high blood pressure is cut to 200
反之假設你高血壓切得200
you will die a lot
你會密死掉很多
That is not high blood pressure is not high blood pressure
那個不是高血壓的不是高血壓
That's what we just talked about
那這個就是我們剛剛講
The sensitivity and specificity
那個敏感度跟特異度
The level of sensitivity and specificity
敏感度跟特異度的高低
It involves what we just said
就是牽涉到我們剛才講的
Positive vs Predicted Value vs Predicted Value
陽性跟預測值跟預測值
What I just said is because we actually have some
剛才講的因為我們實際有些
In fact, it is interlocking
事實上是環環相扣
Back to the fact that it's simple math
這回去事實上這很簡單的數學
In this way, keeping the total number unchanged
這樣把這個總數字不變的情況之下
You still go to that I believe you will understand
你依然去那個我相信就會了解
why? this may be a better answer
為什麼?這也許主意的講會更好的回答
In fact, I have just been in the clinic
其實我剛剛在臨床上
or positive predictive value
或者空溫溫身上陽性預測值
means you may have
就是說你可能有
I might get tested for nasal pregnancy cancer
我可能去做一個檢驗看會不會得鼻孕癌
But what if I say Epstein-Barr virus positive?
但是呢我如果說EB病毒陽性
My chances of actually having nasal pregnancy cancer are maybe 10%
我真的有鼻孕癌的機會可能只有10%
But this 10% is very important to me
但是這10%對我來說是很重要的
Because it is a serious disease that requires early detection and early treatment
因為它是一個很嚴重的疾病需要早期發現早期治療
I would rather
我寧願
Let me tell you that there is a possibility that I have nasal pregnancy cancer
跟大家講說我有鼻孕癌的可能性有
Then I will go for further treatment for nasal pregnancy
然後我再去做鼻孕進的進一步的治療
allow me to get further diagnosis
讓我能夠得到進一步的診斷
So it doesn't matter if the positive predictive value is low
所以陽性預測值低沒有關係
But I'm going to tell someone that you definitely don't have nasal pregnancy cancer.
但是我要跟一個人講說你絕對沒有鼻孕癌
You must never say that the nasal pregnancy cancer he used later
你絕對不可以說他後來用的鼻孕癌
So we sometimes choose a high negative predictive value
所以我們有些時候會選陰性預測值很高
But the positive predictive value is not too high
但是陽性預測值不太高
Because we still have further diagnostic opportunities
因為我們還有進一步診斷機會的時候
We can use something like this
我們可以用這樣的方法
to carry out
來進行
that this
那這個
I think this one we wait maybe we can try again
我想這個我們等一下也許可以再
again
再來
try it and talk
試一下再來談一下
Just now there is another question, isn't it?
剛才還有一個問題是不是
No, there is another lady coming
沒有後面還有一個小姐來
Excuse me
不好意思
consult
請教
vice director
副所長
That's an average room
那個這是房間的一個一般的
all the troubles of women
婦女所有的困擾
That is to say, most girls after menopause
就是說大部分一個女生在停經以後
there are two
那有兩種有的
The associate doctor will advise him to take hormones
副科醫生會建議他說吃荷爾蒙
Then some doctors suggested not to take hormones
那有的醫生又建議說不可以吃荷爾蒙
That
那
The reason for suggesting not to take hormones is
建議不吃荷爾蒙他們的理由是
explain
說
you may get it if you eat it
吃了可能會得
right
對
That
那
The first person who took hormones because of you
最早以前因為你吃荷爾蒙的人啊
they usually
他們通常都會
In the end, it will cause the devil in the womb
到最後就會造成子宮內魔真身
What about the devil in the womb?
那子宮內魔真身呢
The method used by doctors before
那以前的醫生就用的方法
That is to say, do a uterine scraping action
就是說做一個刮子宮的動作
then it's ok
然後就OK了
So the doctor also said
所以以前醫生也說
If you eat it, you may return to uterine cancer
吃了有可能回子宮癌
Now it's breast cancer
那現在又說是乳癌
what is the relationship between these two
這個兩個有什麼關係
please teach me
請教一下
We don't have very complex inquiries from here
我們從這沒有很複雜的詢問
What is the role of hormones?
剛才講荷爾蒙的角色是什麼
Sudden death breast real body
就是猝死乳房真身嘛
But another role for hormones
可是荷爾蒙的另外一個角色
Assuming hormones are true if not good
假設荷爾蒙真的如果不好的話
Then we don't need hormones long ago
那我們老早就不要荷爾蒙
Why hormones control body temperature
為什麼荷爾蒙控制體溫
Educational real estate stocks say
育房股直輸說
Why does a person have a fever after menopause
一個人停經之後為什麼會發燒
red face
臉部炒紅
Why eat that after menopause
為什麼停經之後要吃那個
The so-called hormone replacement therapy
那個所謂的荷爾蒙替代療法
HRT
HRT
Because some people after menopause
因為有些人停經之後
You will feel the nausea, vomiting and fried red just mentioned
會覺得剛才講的噁心嘔吐炒紅
It's hard
很難受嘛
So when standing in the objective point of the sub-factory
所以站在副廠客觀點的時候
Then you make it up?
那你就補回來嘛
But to make up for it, judging from the benchmark just now
可是補回來從剛才的基準來看
it's easy
就很容易
That promotes cell proliferation that leads to breast cancer
那促使細胞增生會得乳癌
Therefore the same
因此同樣的
The concept of personalized medicine was born
個人化醫學的概念就產生了
Who will eat properly
到底誰吃得會恰如其分
so just right
所以剛剛好
This is what we are studying now
這就是我們現在研究的
that is
就是
just a word
一言而已
HRT words
HRT的話
some people eat very fast
有些人吃的是長很快
Some people just happen to grow up to that twenty
有些人是恰巧長到那個二十
won't get breast cancer
不會得乳癌
But it can prevent a person
可是可以預防一個人
That word still has a lot of research points of view
那個字還有很多研究的觀點
in terms of food
那就食物面而言
Now you ask the surgeon to
現在你問外科醫師跟
Obstetricians have different views
副產科醫師的觀點都不一樣
because
因為
practically
實際來看
This hormone replacement therapy
這種賀爾蒙替代療法
The risk of breast cancer is
得乳癌的危險性是
1.3 times more than not eating
比沒有吃多1.3倍
Equal to 1.3 is 0.3 more than 1
等於是1.3比1多0.3
His obstetrics department must tell you
他副產科一定跟你講
Secondhand smoke is twice as likely to cause breast cancer
二手菸是兩倍多得乳癌
often speak
常常講
You are not afraid of your husband smoking.
你先生抽菸你都不怕了
Why are you afraid that HRT will get breast cancer?
你還怕什麼那個HRT會得乳癌
So the surgeon said
所以外科醫師就講說
important risk factor
那麼重要危險因子
you dare to eat
你還敢吃
So the surgeon with
所以外科醫師跟
The concept of negative productivity revolution is different
負產革命這個觀點就不一樣
Of course we most hope that our scientists
當然我們最希望就是我們科學家
So the conclusion is not to eat subtleties, right?
所以結論還是不吃微妙是不是
Do not eat subtle
不吃微妙 從基轉上來看不吃微妙
But some people just feel uncomfortable, so what should I do?
可是有些人就是很不舒服啊 那怎麼辦
Let's eat for that negative productivity revolution
那為那個負產革命吃一吃吧
Then check it a few more times, that is, people do photography every two years
那就多檢查幾次嘛 就是人家是兩年做一次攝影
You do it every six months now, not to mention that some people may have breasts
你現在半年做一次 更何況有些人也許是乳房
Before the cure, there was a cover point, as I said just now
還沒有治癒前就有蓋化點 就剛才的話
Then you'd better not eat it because you are a high-risk situation
那你就最好不要吃 因為你是屬於高危險情
Then this is where the concept of personalized medicine comes in.
那這就是個人化醫學的概念就倒進來了
Then we'd like to do some more genetic testing.
那我們就希望再做一些基因的檢查
I found that whoever eats it will be just right
發現說誰吃是會剛剛好的
That's where we scientists haven't worked hard enough
那就是我們科學家還努力不夠的地方
That is also the related one followed by
那也是相關的一個接在後面
That is to say, the hormone itself is released after a girl's menopause
就是說荷爾蒙本身在女生停經以後
She'll increase yours just by taking that hormone
她會增加你的 就是吃那個荷爾蒙的話
would increase your hormone production, right?
會增加你的荷爾蒙的產生嘛 對不對
Hormones are equivalent to a power source of a human body
那荷爾蒙等於說一個人體的一個電源一樣的
you must have this hormone
你必須要有這個荷爾蒙
Only then can many things in your body function more normally
才可以讓你的身體很多東西運作比較正常
so it's good to say
所以說起來是好的
is it possible
那有是不是可以
For example, after a girl shuts down
譬如說一個女生在停機以後
she's been on hormones for a while
她吃過一段時間的荷爾蒙
nothing happened
也沒有什麼事
Then she felt bored and didn't bother to eat.
那後來她覺得很煩了就懶得吃了
too lazy to eat
懶得吃了
another ten years
再過了十年
She felt that there was the situation that caused the shutdown before
她又覺得有產生那個以前停機的那個狀況
For example, the heartbeat is a little irregular
譬如說心跳有一點不整
or sarcasm or bad sleep or something
或者有嘲諷或者睡眠不好什麼之類
Can she still eat and drink at this time?
這種時候她是不是還可以再去吃喝嗎
sure
當然可以
So this one uses the same more honorable medical concept
所以這個是用同樣的那個更榮耀醫學概念
Let's compare two groups
我們就比兩組嘛
One group is to taunt after shutdown
一組是停機之後會嘲諷
One group will not taunt after shutdown
一組是停機之後不會嘲諷
It costs 4,000 yuan to do it
來做花四千塊
4,000 yuan for a group energy scan
四千塊錢做群精力掃描
Let's see where the mocking gene is
來看嘲諷的基因在哪裡
then you can decide to say
那就可以決定說
who should eat and who should not eat
誰應該吃誰不應該吃
So a lot of the concepts we're talking about today
所以很多這種我們今天講的概念
It's actually very simple
事實上是都很簡單
Our cost determination
我們那個藉由成本的下定
Advances in technology, many things that were not possible before
技術的進步 很多以前沒有辦法達到的事情
able to make better predictions
能夠做更好的預測
This is where our medical scientists work hard
這是我們醫學家努力的地方
That is to say, it still depends on the person
那就是說還是要因人而已
because of people
是因人而已
People with conditions can eat it
就是有狀況的人就可以吃
Yes, the straight line is just saying eat tomatoes, okay?
對 那直線的只是說吃番茄好不好
Of course it's good. Do you want to eat five or ten or one?
當然好 那要吃五顆還是十顆還是一顆
Everyone is different
每一個人不一樣啊
Scientists hope to put that
科學家就希望把那個
Find out the genes that are different for each person
每一個人不一樣的基因找出來
OK thank you
OK 謝謝
pregene sequencing
前基因的定序
About every three to five years
大概在各個三五年
Just drop from 300,000 to 30,000
就從三十萬降到三萬塊
Now technology is advancing rapidly
現在科技進步很快
the future is like
那未來就像
when did you say it
什麼時候講的
In fact, he emphasized that the latter is very important
其實他強調後面一個很重要的
When the influence of this gene is very small
當這個基因的影響度很少的時候
Most diseases are genetic
大部分的疾病都是基因
Effects of interacting with the environment
跟環境互動的影響
For example, eating foods high in sterol
譬如說吃檔固醇含量很高的
but my steroid metabolizing genes
可是我的檔固醇代謝的基因
are different
是不一樣的
Then this reactivation is very important
那這個複動就很重要
i have bad genes for example
我有壞的基因舉個例子
i used to do
我以前做
If a person eats aflatoxin
如果一個人他吃的黃曲毒醇
will get liver cancer
會得肝癌
But if it has a good read gene
但是如果它有一個很好的解讀基因
If it is called GSTM1T1
叫做GSTM1T1的話
No matter how much toxin it has
它黃具毒素再多
it read it all
它都解讀掉了
It won't get liver cancer
它都不會得肝癌
this kind of person
這種人就
Exotics
天賦異品
It doesn't matter what he eats
他怎麼吃都沒關係
but if your genes are bad
但是如果你的基因不好
If there is no way to understand
那沒有辦法解讀的話
then please don't eat
那請你就不要吃
Things that contain aflatoxin
含有黃具毒素的東西
So what about the future?
所以未來呢
it's more about the environment
就更多的是環境
The influence of interactions with genes
跟基因的交互作用的影響
what you just said
那剛才你講的
Hormonal factors are the same
荷爾蒙的因素也是一樣
if we know
如果我們知道
Hormone basics in the human body
荷爾蒙基礎人體裡面
he in different women
他在不同的女性
he has different genes
他因為不同的基因
his that
他的那個
Manifestations of stalled syndrome
停進症候群的表現
not the same
也不一樣
Then if we understand more and more
那如果我們越來越了解
then we can
那我們就能夠
tailor-made for everyone
為每一個人量身訂做
How much hormone should he take
他荷爾蒙應該吃多少
at what stage should you eat
應該在什麼階段吃
if after a while
如果停了一段時間以後
what happened again
又碰到什麼
At what stage should you eat
又該在什麼階段吃
then if by that time
那如果到那個時候的話
Well, medicine can help you a lot.
那醫學就給大家有很大的幫助嘛
So let's all look forward to the day
所以讓大家期待有一天
We can all learn more about ourselves
我們大家都能夠對自己更了解
know more about the environment
對環境也更了解這樣
ok because of time
好 因為時間的關係
I think we can first thank Deputy Director Shen
我想我們就先謝謝沈副所長
Then he will stay later
那他等一下會留下來
I have some personal questions to ask
還有一些私人的問題要問的話
it's ok
也可以啦
Okay, let's applaud him again and thank him.
好 那我們再次鼓掌謝謝他
Thanks
謝謝